<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Humble proposals for the relief, encouragement, security and happiness of the loyal, couragious seamen of England, in their lives and payment, in the service of our Most Gracious King William, and the defence of these nations humbly presented to the two most Honourable Houses, the Lords and Commons of England, in Parliament assembled / by a faithful subject of His Majesty, and servant to the Parliament and nation, and the seamen of England, in order for safety and security of all aforesaid, W. Hodges ; to which is added, a dialogue concerning the art of ticket-buying, in a discourse between Honesty, Poverty, Cruelty and Villany, concerning that mystery of iniquity, and ruin of the loyal seamen.</title>
            <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12185431</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12185431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 603:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Humble proposals for the relief, encouragement, security and happiness of the loyal, couragious seamen of England, in their lives and payment, in the service of our Most Gracious King William, and the defence of these nations humbly presented to the two most Honourable Houses, the Lords and Commons of England, in Parliament assembled / by a faithful subject of His Majesty, and servant to the Parliament and nation, and the seamen of England, in order for safety and security of all aforesaid, W. Hodges ; to which is added, a dialogue concerning the art of ticket-buying, in a discourse between Honesty, Poverty, Cruelty and Villany, concerning that mystery of iniquity, and ruin of the loyal seamen.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 63.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy.</term>
               <term>Sailors --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HUMBLE PROPOSALS FOR THE Relief, Encouragement, Security and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Loyal, Couragious Seamen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in their Lives and Payment, in the Service of our Moſt Gracious King <hi>William,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>Humbly Preſented to the Two Moſt Honourable Houſes, the Lords and Commons of <hi>England,</hi> in Parliament Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>By a Faithful Subject of his Majeſty, and Servant to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Nation, and the Seamen of <hi>England;</hi> in order for Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Security of all aforeſaid, <hi>W. Hodges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, A DIALOGUE concerning the Art of Ticket-buying.</p>
            <p>In a Diſcourſe between <hi>Honesty, Poverty, Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Villany.</hi> concerning that Myſtery of Iniquity, and Ruin of the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Seamen.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55757:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55757:2"/>
            <head>To the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament Aſſembled, Humbly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</head>
            <p>THAT the Providence of our moſt gracious God, having ſtirred me up to ſee, and conſider, and lament the moſt dreadful Ruin and Deſtruction of the Loyal Seamen of <hi>England,</hi> in their Lives and Pay, that ever theſe Nations did behold, and to Repreſent the ſame in all Humility to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and conſidering alſo, that ſome of their Miſeries were, in my Judgment, againſt Grace, and Reaſon and Common Senſe; and alſo ſometimes againſt thoſe other Four Things that uſed to be eſteemed of as Jewels in <hi>England;</hi> that is, Religion, Liberty, Property, and their Lives: To ſay nothing of the Fifth, without Law, made me to dread the Conſequent; and I did obſerve that it was hidden from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and your Honours ſo long, until there was the Loſs, as I repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, of the Lives of above Forty Thouſand, and of the Pay of above Sixty Thouſand of them; and if there had been occaſion to queſtion the Truth of it, I would have proved at any time by the King's Books, in twenty Four Days time, without Two Pence Charge to the King or Nation; and conſidering that his Majeſty has ſpoken for their Relief, and your Honours, who had raiſed money enough before to have kept them from Ruin, and to have ſpared a Million or Two of it by Capt. <hi>St. Lo</hi>'s Rule.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if they had been but managed as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seamen were in former days, and as the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> do at this day, to ſave near half their money, and moſt of their Seamens Lives. But I ſay, Your Honours being now alſo Reſolved to ſtudy their Relief, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, in all Humility, to caſt in my Mite alſo. Now, in order to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55757:3"/>ſame, which I would intreat your Honours to accept of, as Rough and Unframed Timber, to be ſquared and fitted to what part your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours pleaſe; and one thing is, many crooked pieces are made uſe of in the building of Shipping, that when placed aright not only ſerve to ſtrengthen the Ship, and help to preſerve the Lives of the Seamen, but formally uſe to help tohold the Ships together, while they daily beat their Enemies; and tho theſe Pieces may not be always ſo readily known to all Landmen, I will preſume ſome may ſerve now, and ſome another time.</p>
            <p>And I do aſſure your Honours, if I had better at hand, I would preſent them to you: But they are my own, and ſo ſaved me the trouble of begging, borrowing, or which is worſe, ſtealing; and I intreat your Honours Patience; for their Miſeries being ſo dreadful, and ſo many years a growing, and ſo many times Ten Thouſands, as they could not have been eaſily repreſented, except one ſhould have ſaid, their Caſe was almoſt all together Miſerable: But bleſſed be God that it is not: They have a good King and good Countrey for their Friends, if their Caſes are not blinded from them: And as to their Remedies, it requires a great deal of Care and Inquiry: And when I look back to what I repreſented before; and forward, to what ſtrange need there is of them now, and when I hear that a great many there is that are in Droves, travelling in other Countries without Shooes or Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſeeking to enter into the Service of the Merchants of <hi>England</hi> there, or to ſerve other Nations, and Run away from che Merchant-Ships alſo, and loſe their Pay, ſome of them not being willing to come home, for fear of the Preſs; This makes my Heart dread the Effects of it, and do ſuppoſe theſe Two Things would be worth while to be inquired into by the Parliament, to know how the Caſe ſtands with them in theſe reſpects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let every Man of War's Book, that hath been in the <hi>Streights,</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Portugal,</hi> be ſearched, to ſee what Numbers Run away out of any Ship, or every Ship, at any Port or Place.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> To have an Account of the Men of War and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships loſt this Eighteen Months to the <hi>French,</hi> with the whole Number of Men taken in each Ship, and in the whole Shipping loſt; and then have alſo the Number of Men return'd from <hi>France</hi> in that time, that did belong to thoſe Ships, and what is wanting may be ſuppoſed to be entred into the <hi>French</hi> Service, if not dead; and if
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55757:3"/>of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships taken, there be come home ſhort, near an Hundred of thoſe men that were taken; it is to be fear'd, the reſt will ſtay until warm weather, and then get ſome Money and Cloaths, if our Preſs is ſo great this Winter, that they meet the poor Captive Wretches when they Return home in their Louſie Cloaths from <hi>France,</hi> and beg their way near an Hundred and Fifty Miles; then before they come to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> catch them, and carry them on Board, Rags and Lice, as they Run; put them down in the Hold of the Veſſel, to lie on the Boards or Ballaſt, or what they pleaſe, if they be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bedding; and as Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> ſaid, <hi>if they periſh, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Notable Age to tame Prodigals in, if they be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Seamen; but if they be Double-Pay Officers, then it may be they Run up and down, and be as bad or worſe than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and ſo it may be will not be worth, ſome of them, a Groat a Dozen, when the War is over; tho they moſt times Live; For the Officers that have Liberty to come on Shore, die very few of them. But this by the way. But I am too large in the Introduction.</p>
            <p>I did think to ſay ſomething more as to the Seamen's Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, in this Preface; as that without the Seamen be paid off yearly on Shore, and have a Fortnight's or Month's Liberty to Recruit their Healths, I am afraid they will never be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to come into the Service, neither ſtay there; and if they do, and die, it is as bad as Running; for if they Run away in <hi>England,</hi> and the Merchants get them, it is an help to Trade, and the King may have them again; and I could never know the Reaſon of that pretence of keeping the Seamen in ſuch ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very in their payments, in this Age more than any other, to be paid on Board; as if his Majeſty's Service was not as good as in any Age of the World. For my part, I ſay, according to the money raiſed, there could never have been better Pay for the Seamen in the world. And indeed I would not have the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England</hi> ſay Juſtly, That God and the King ſent good Meat, but the Devil ſent them Cooks that ſpoil'd it half in dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55757:4"/>
            <p>But in ſhort, I cannot ſee how the Nation, in the general, can anſwer the Seamen's being left to Ruin:</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> as I ſaid, it is againſt Grace, againſt the gracious Law of Chriſt, not to do to them as we would others ſhould do to us; which is taught the Children in their Catechiſms.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is againſt the gracious Providence of God to theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who did, by a Miracle, ſend over our gracious King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> to be a means to ſecure our Religion, Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; and if the Nation, who enjoys all theſe in Peace at home, ſhould let the Seamen be Ruined, and loſe all together, and their Lives into the bargain; I am afraid Chriſt will tell us another word in our Ears, That the Scripture ſhall not fail; and the ſame meaſure men mete, ſhall be meted to them again.</p>
            <p>And ſo much to their being managed contrary to Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Contrary to Reaſon; for Reaſon tells us, other Ages en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged their Seamen, and paid them on Shore; and other Nations do ſo now. And Reaſon may tell thoſe who have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Nature of the paying on Board, That the Seamen's Families and Relations have not enjoyed the Benefit of little more than half their Pay, to their Familie's Comfort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is contrary to common ſenſe, to think that if Seamen do uſually die, great part, where they are kept 2 or 3 years on board, that they ſhould have any Policy to keep them until they die, rather than to pay them off, to Recruit their Health and Lives.</p>
            <p>And indeed, who could be ever imagined to come freely into that Service where nothing but Death can part again, and then the Widow denied their Mony oft-times at laſt. And beſides the Loſs of the Seamen's Lives, there is extraordinary Charge to the Nation, and no benefit to the publick; but it may be the Commanders that had abuſed the Seamen all the War, could not get more, and would want a Ship to get Mony in, and ſo might want bread, while our brave Commanders would have Men enough But thoſe who have driven away the Seamen from their Ships, and could have a ſupply by turning over men from other Ships, theſe might be at a Loſs for Men next Year. But my Skill in Sea Affairs is too ſmall: Did it but attain to the heighth of my Faithulneſs to his Majeſty, and Love to my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, I would, if the Lord aſſiſted me with Life and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55757:4"/>Health, write ſuch an Hiſtory of the Knavery, Folly, Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, Treachery, Ruin and Deſtruction of this War; in the Sea-Affairs, the Land would admire at; and would write eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Line, to the beſt of my Judgment, what would be found true, not only in another Age, where they will ſpeak plainly, how his Majeſty, and the Parliament, and Nation, and Merchants are cheated and abuſed. But I would write what I believe will be found true in the Day of Judgment, where all Cloaks will be thrown off; and then it will be known, that God did not ſend Mankind into the world to be like Fiſhes, the great ones to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the little ones; and I bleſs the Lord, who kept me from being one of the Devourers of the Age; for I have had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity with eaſe to be a Monſter, when I laid out an hundred Pound a week, or two, in Seamen's Pay, if I had bought at half Profit, or Twelve Shillings in the Pound Profit, as ſome Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters did, I ſhould have doubled my Mony ſo often, to have been able to have ſwallowed up 3 or 4 Seamen's Pay for a Breakfaſt, beſides what <hi>I</hi> had for Dinner and Supper; and then <hi>I</hi> ſhould never have ſaid a word of the Ruin of the Seamen, but ſhould have been forc'd to have kept all Counſel, if the King had been cheated of a quarter of his Money, and the Seamen of above half their pay.</p>
            <p>But I preſume it will be well to look back to the moſt happy ſtate of our Ships of War, when we did moſt effectually beat our Enemies, and incourage our Seamen, and ſee if we do not find the neglect of their method hath been the Loſs of half our Seamen, and many of our Ships.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether their way was not to go out in the Summer, and take all Opportunities to ſight and deſtroy their Enemies, and come in again with the <hi>greateſt part of the Fleet,</hi> and pay off <hi>the Seamen,</hi> and ſave <hi>their Lives and Pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether if this had been done, the Seamen would not have been incouraged to <hi>come freely into the King's Service,</hi> as in other Ages, as into a place where there was Mony, and Liberty, and Releaſe, and not perpetual Bondage. And if at laſt diſcharged by reaſon of Sickneſs, and had Tickets ſigned by all the ſigning Officers, for the ſame to be deprived, otherwiſe cheated publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their mony, to the ſhame of the Pay, and the Ruin of the diſcharged; and whether any can now, on the laſt Terms,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55757:5"/>be ſafe to ſerve their King and Country: and it may be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, whether it be not a ſhameful thing, when poor Seamen have had their Pay received by falſe Powers, they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the ſight of the Ship's Books, to ſee who received it; and therefore whether alſo this, and the denying them otherwiſe the knowledg of their Caſe, be not an unjuſt and unreaſonable thing to let poor Creatures be Cheated and Ruined, and hide it from them. And what advantage it is to the Government, to let their poor Seamen be ſo managed, beſides the King's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at extraordinary Charge to pay them ſo far from <hi>London,</hi> and the City deprived of the benefit of taking their mony, as in other Ages, wherein the City of <hi>London</hi> was not uſed to be ſo ſlighted, neither the Seamen ſo Ruined.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall preſume to ſay more in the Body of my Book; for whoever pleaſeth to read it at their leiſure, what my Thoughts are; and if the Honourable Houſes pardon me, I ſhall not need much to trouble my ſelf with the Offences any others may take at it; for I write for good, and not to pleaſe, but to hinder Cheating the King, and Ruining the Seamen; and not to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe that would have it all ſmuggled up in ſilence; which makes me think of one lately, that becauſe he could not find any thing falſe in my book, had this ſuppoſition, and that was, That he ſuppoſed if I had Repreſented ſo much in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King would have hanged me.</p>
            <p>Now to that, being only a Suppoſition, I will anſwer it with other Suppoſitions: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I muſt have been a Fool or a Knave to have writ it, if I did not conſult before I writ it, whether I could, with a good Conſcience, have ſuffered Death for the ſame; and if I could, that might have been an eaſier Death than the Stone or the Gout. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſuppoſe, by his Leave, if the <hi>French</hi> King's Subjects are Ruined and Deſtroyed, it is by his Knowledge and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and not Ruined and deſtroyed without his knowledge, and the knowledge of his Nobles, as I preſume our Seamen's Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are hid from the King and Parliament, and the blame muſt at laſt lie ſomewhere; and it may be the next Age will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at ſhe Hiſtory of it; therefore I take pains to inform the King and Parliament, that they may let the blame and ſhame be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55757:5"/>laid on thoſe who have been Unjuſt, and Cruel, and Barbarous in the management of the Ruined Seamen and their Families: And indeed I ſuppoſe alſo,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>French</hi> King, tho he plagues almoſt all Mankind, yet he incourages his Seamen, let's them come on ſhore every Year, and mony in their Pocket; lends them his Men of War to Privateer in, gives them his Tenths; and in ſhort, if they have gotten Three Millions of Riches this Year from us, his Seamen's Share is more Hundreds of Thouſands of Pounds than would pay our Ruined Seamen all their Q's and R's.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe if he had ſeen his Seamen had been half dead, or frightned away, or Cheated of their Pay, and he not known it before-hand, <hi>I</hi> proteſt <hi>I</hi> do not only ſuppoſe, but really conclude they would have been more likely to have hang'd ſome that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined his Seamen, for being Knaves to do it; and thoſe that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med honeſt, for being Tools to conſent to it; and that might have eſcaped well next time, or at leaſt had as good Quarter for telling as they for acting.</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſe one Suppoſition more, That if the <hi>French</hi> King did know that his Admiralty, and Navy-Board, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of Ships did Ruin and deſtroy his Seamen's Lives and Pay, the Seamen would not ſo conſtantly go home to <hi>France</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as they do; neither would he have Men enough to man his Fleet; neither would any other means ſecure his Seamen's Lives and Pay, without Managers that were as merciful to them as good men are to their Beaſts, who do not let them groan and cry, and languiſh away for want of that Provender that is due to them for their Labour, for that day's work wherein they fell ſick under their Burden, which is too ſad, and too tedious to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large on.</p>
            <p>And if your Honours think it to be too tedious, it may be conſidered, That the Miſeries of the Seamen in <hi>England,</hi> have been of more various Kinds, and peradventure various Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers than the Miſeries of all the Corporations of <hi>England,</hi> and cannot be Repreſented in a few Words; beſides all their other Miſeries of their Families that they are ſubject to, equal with the loſt of Mankind; And as their Diſeaſes are many, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire honeſt faithful Doctors, in order to their Cure, and not leave them in the hands of hard hearted Wretches, to Ruin
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55757:6"/>them. But <hi>I</hi> could write until <hi>I</hi> tire your Honours and my ſelf. But <hi>I</hi> beg your Honour's Gracious Pardon, and do lay my ſelf at your Honour's Feet, and beg of God to give his Majeſty Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as an Angel of God; and that God would fill your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours with all Wiſdom, and that in his and your Proſperity the Nation may be happy and bleſſed; and then <hi>I</hi> hope <hi>I</hi> ſhall in mercy injoy a ſhare of the ſame; Who ſubſcribe my ſelf a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lover and Servant to his moſt Gracious Majeſty King <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> and all your Honours, and all good men, while <hi>I</hi> remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Hermitage-Bridge, <date>Jan. 44. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Hodges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55757:6"/>
            <head>Propoſals, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Subject of Encouraging and Increaſing of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Seamen, is of greater Conſequence than abundance of Mankind doth readily apprehend; and we being an <hi>Iſland,</hi> cannot be ſafe or happy in Peace or War with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; which makes me admire what ſenſleſs Stuff the Brains of thoſe are, or what hardened metal their Hearts are, that have ſo greatly Ruined and Oppreſſed many of them and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; and <hi>I</hi> have admired and lamented with Tears, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Ruin: And if God himſelf commanded the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo ſtrictly, <hi>That if they ſaw their Enemie's Ox or Aſs fall down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Burden, they ſhould help them up;</hi> Then God forbid I ſhould have my Heart harder than a <hi>Jew,</hi> that when I ſee not my Enemie's Aſſes, but my moſt gracious Soveraign King <hi>William's,</hi> and my dear Country's Seamen, many dead under their burdens, and others in Ditches of miſery, if I ſhould not endeavour to help them up, I ſhould be worſe than a <hi>Jew.</hi> And I conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſeeing their miſeries thrown on them, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Years to help them out, until I did almoſt fall in my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> cried out for help to their Maſter and Dame, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent a large ſupply of Mony to their Managers and Drivers, to aſſiſt them and help them up; and at firſt they had help. But the poor Cattle being kept travelling ſo long, until they fell ſick by Droves; and when they that drove them ſaw they were ſick, and could be drove no farther, either let them die with the Load on their backs, but if others let them out to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55757:7"/>Paſture, then there was an Order, That if they could not be well, to come into the ſame Drove in 28 Days, they muſt then run the hazard to loſe all the Hay and Corn due to them and their Young; altho it may be many of them died within a few Days after they were in Paſture; or it may be the Drove, they belonged to, was gone 300 miles before they were well; and it may be they went into the next Drove of their Maſters they met with, if they lived, and were well; or it may be they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſick, and were ſent into ſome Stable for Cure, and there did continue long after their Drivers had ruined the Reſt of their Fother: And I conſidering what a Scarcity of others to bear the Burdens, and ſo Extraordinary Charge to buy more, that I thought it better to keep them there was, and prevent that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and Charge, eſpecially conſidering beſides, That it was a ſign of mens being wicked, whoſe tender mercies were cruel; And alſo, that the young ones they bought, did many times die before they were a Year uſed to the Pack-Saddle.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, I dreamed, That without there were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, faithful Managers, Drivers and Hoſtlers, the poor Cattle would be ruined at laſt.</p>
            <p>But I had need to beg pardon for telling ſo much of my Dream: <hi>I</hi> will forbear the reſt; for perhaps it would be an hour longer, and they that underſtand the interpretation, find it all true.</p>
            <p>But now for the Seamen's Encouragement to ſerve his Majeſty, <hi>I</hi> will propoſe ſome few things, always provided, That if <hi>I</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch and ſuch honeſt ways and means, it may not be miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: As for Example, if <hi>I</hi> ſay, that there muſt be good Commanders, and honeſt Purſers, or they will be miſerable at laſt, and run away indeed, many of them. This muſt not be underſtood as if <hi>I</hi> were ſo uncharitable as to reflect on all in thoſe Places; for we have ſome Worthy Admirals and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, whoſe Names <hi>I</hi> honour, and who will neither abuſe the Seamen themſelves, neither ſuffer their Officers to abuſe them; and for every honeſt Purſer <hi>I</hi> love them.</p>
            <p>But my Head being ſo like a Land-Flood, over-flowing with the laſt Stormy Times of Miſery and Knavery, that ſome of it will overflow the Banks before <hi>I</hi> can get any Materials ready to ſecure the Country from a further inundation.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55757:7"/>
            <p>And now <hi>I</hi> will begin to propoſe ſome Materials that <hi>I</hi> do ſuppoſe will be uſeful, in order for ſecurity for time to come; and that which is uſeful may be made uſe of now or hereafter, as Times mend: How long they have been bad, God knows. But <hi>I</hi> remember, many Years paſt, it was ſaid, <hi>Bad Men made Bad Times:</hi> how it is now, muſt be left to the Learned to Judge. And it was ſaid, <hi>Bad Times cauſed Good Laws;</hi> God ſend the Seamen ſome Token of the Truth of that before they are all ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined.</p>
            <p>And now as to the firſt Conſideration of the Seamen's Relief, it is to be conſidered of the Admiralty and Navy-Board: if they be the moſt Excellent Men in <hi>England</hi> for Loyalty to his preſent Majeſty, and Care of his Men of War and Merchant-Ships, and to preſerve the Seamen's Lives and Pay, that will, it may be, be half a Cure. But if ever there ſhould be in <hi>England,</hi> for time to come, an Admiralty and Navy-board that ſhould be one part falſe and Treacherous, and the other ſoft, and eaſy, and fooliſh, to be led into ignorance and madneſs, it might perhaps lie in their power to put in ſeveral Cowardly, Sorry, Damming Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that would Ruin and Drive away Thouſands of Seamen, and never fight One Enemy; and if there were abundance of good Commanders and Officers that loved the Seamen, and would fight their Enemies, and protect their Friends, they might be tied up as ſo many Cats, ſome in one Room, and ſome in another; and the Mice might play up and down in all the reſt of the Rooms, and alſo devour half the Victuals and Cloaths in ſome Rooms, and be never hurt hardly; Or indeed, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> there might be Ships of War have Orders to lie in the <hi>Downs,</hi> and their Enemie's Ships might come within TwoLeagues of them, and it may be ſnatch away a Merchant-man, and be gone: And if the others ſay, <hi>Their Orders is to lie there, and they muſt not break their Orders;</hi> that may ſerve; or if there ſhould be a Spuadron ordered to lie before <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> to keep their Ships from coming out, and the <hi>French</hi> did ſtart out, and ours had no Orders to follow them, then it may be they might take ſome more <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Ships; I think they took Four <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Ships laſt time, the next day, as near as I can remember; And I deal plainly, becauſe I write not either for Profit, Praiſe, or Preferment; and ſo would do as a Lawyer or Phyſician, that giveth Law or Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55757:8"/>to a Friend freely, giveth the beſt Advice and Help they can poſſible, to have done the ſooner, and perfect the Cure ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually.</p>
            <p>And now having ſaid, it may be, too much to the firſt, <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, only obſerving, by the way, how it is poſſible we Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>London</hi> may be ſerved when we put our Children to Nurſe; We may pay the beſt prices in the World to the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and if they be not honeſt, the Children may be ſtarved at laſt, if we do not go, or ſend to ſee how they are uſed; and if there be good Milk provided for them, it may fall out, that the Nurſe, or her Children, or Servant, yea the very Mongril Dog of the Houſe may devour it three quarters up, with as much greedineſs as ever a Ticket-Buyer bought a Seaman's Pay, Seven Pound Ten Shillings for Forty Shillings, and as much honeſty as ever a poor Seaman was made Run baſely and ſhamefully out of his Pay at the Office, or at Pay-day.</p>
            <p>2. Therefore if the Seamen ſhould, or would be ever encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, we ſhould look back to the Juſtice, Policy and Honeſty of our Fore-fathers, who uſed to pay their Seamen their Mony on Shore; and the Commanders, and Seamen, and Ships, uſed to be agreed together to fight and Ruin, and deſtroy their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at Sea; and God bleſſed their honeſt Courage, and their honeſt Pay; and every Seaman's Life then loſt at Sea, was as a Poyſonous Arrow to their Enemies: They kill'd their Enemies, and deſtroy'd their Fleets and Seamen; and they that lived came in and were paid; and thoſe that died, had their money, paid their Friends, and Bounty-money ſometimes alſo; and this did buſineſs.</p>
            <p>And there is theſe Two Things to be conſidered of, which of them ſhewed moſt Courage, moſt Policy, moſt Profit or moſt Loſs, our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet neglecting or refuſing to fall upon the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, when God from Heaven turned the Wind fair for our Fleet to fall on the <hi>French,</hi> when they were in <hi>Freſh-Water-Bay,</hi> on our own Coaſt; When, in all likelihood, God that gave us the Wind to fall on them, would have given us the Victory, and then we might have Ruined their Fleet on our own Coaſt, if we had fought as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships uſed to do when <hi>I</hi> was a Boy, and it may be not loſt 4 Ships, neither Two Thouſand Seamen in the Fight, becauſe God ſeemed to turn the Wind for our Fleet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55757:8"/>to fight, as he did for our gracious King <hi>William</hi> to Land at firſt, and Crowned his Induſtry and Courage: And whether if our moſt Gracious and Valiant King <hi>William</hi> had been afraid to have fallen on his Enemies at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> becauſe of danger to have ſaved ſome hundred Men's Lives, then he might not have loſt the Victory, and had forty Thouſand Men's Lives dwindled away by Sickneſs and Skambling Fights in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince, and it may be, the War continued there until this day, as it doth at Sea; but bleſſed be God, who gave him Courage and Victory, and to every Man he loſt there, he Ruined ten Enemies, and Ruined their whole Cauſe in the Concluſion in that Nation; and had our Fleet done ſo, what Mercy had <hi>England</hi> enjoyed, to have ſeen the <hi>French</hi> Fleet Ruined.</p>
            <p>But now as to our Ships and Men, and the two Queſtions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Whether it was greater Profit to the Nation and Seamen to ſave their Ships and Men, as aforeſaid, and of looſing four Ships, than in Fighting our Enemies Yard-Arm, and Yard-Arm, with all our Fleet, after the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> way of Fighting, as old <hi>Blake,</hi> and old <hi>Dean,</hi> and old <hi>Albemarle</hi> uſed to do, if their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were twice their Number. But now inſtead of that, we ſaved our Ships and Men then, and loſt twenty times four Ships ſince, and twenty times two thouſand Seamen ſince, and great part of them deſtroyed not their Enemies by the Bargain; and which is beſt or worſt I leave to thoſe who have more Skill than I to Judge. But in ſhort, if the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> be ever truly incouraged and preſerved for time to come, they muſt be paid on Shore, and it muſt be ſo contrived as near as poſſible, that every Man may be paid off once in a Year, or tw<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, and have then a little ſecurity againſt the Preſs, that they may Recruit their Healths, and then they will be incouraged to come into the Service again, and their Friends glad to ſend them; and without that, I am afraid other incouragements will be but like a few Oats ſhewed a Horſe to tempt him to come and take up a Pack, who remembers the laſt time he could never get it off before he fell ſick, and was thrown in the Hedg: And laſtly, although he ſaw a great part of his Companions Dyed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55757:9"/>their Burdens, none would be ſo merciful to them as to give them a Fortnight's Reſt in ſeveral Years. This may ſeem a fooliſh Compariſon, but Children and Fools are ſaid to tell truth. and ſo much to that, if there be no certain time when Seamen ſhall be diſcharged, I fear there will be no certainty of their coming in for time to come freely: And ſo much to that.</p>
            <p>3ly, If His Majeſty, and the two moſt Honourable Houſes would advance all able Seamen's Pay four or five Shillings the Month, this might be the way to incourage the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> to ſerve more chearfully and freely.</p>
            <p>4thly, All ordinary Seamen's Pay, but two Shillings the Month, that they might all ſtrive to be Able Seamen.</p>
            <p>5thly, That all Apprentiſes might be incouraged when they are Honeſt, and Puniſhed when they are not; that is, their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to have twelve Shillings the Month, and they themſelves the remainder; that is, if they are ſuch as deſerve but Eighteen Shillings the Month, to have Four Shillings themſelves to buy them Cloaths; if Men, to be Paid Nine Shillings; and if an Able Seaman, to be Paid the Remainder of the Pay, as Able Seamen are; and this I Propoſe. becauſe I have known ſeveral Apprentiſes ſhifting, and running to and fro from Ships, have Beggered their Maſters and Dames, and the King loſeth their Service at laſt, it may be, as their Maſters and Dames do their Pay. But if they had Encouragement themſelves, it may be they would ſtay in their Ships; and if they did not, to be liable to ſerve their Time over again, or pay for it; and alſo by this means it would be certain who ſhould have their Pay; and that hath not been this War; Sometimes the Prentices ſhall have all, and the Maſters none; and ſometimes their Maſters all, and the Prentices may ſtarve for Bread or Cloaths, their Maſters, it may be, ſome of them, taking little care where they ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for when ſick and almoſt naked.</p>
            <p>6. See all Seamen to be encouraged to be able Seamen, and Midſhip-men and Officers, as they are capable of; and not let any Captain's Boys receive Midſhip-men's Pay for their Maſters, and the Brave, Couragious, Loyal Seamen, that ſerved indeed for Midſhip-men to be paid but as Able, or to be ſplit their Pay, one Midſhip-man's Pay between Two Men; and this would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all Seamen that have Brains and Art, to ſtrive for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55757:9"/>and not have Lieutenants put over them, that never ſaw a Gun fired in anger, it may be, this War.</p>
            <p>7. As few Seamen as poſſible to be turn'd from Ship to Ship; and if they are, to have Tickets given them for their former Ships, and theſe to be as Land-marks for their Pay, and not to be made Run afterwards; but ſent up to the Office for their Wives, or Friends, or Parents to receive their mony; and theſe turn'd over Tickets to be Regiſtred, and paid in courſe, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three months at fartheſt, after the turning over; and none to buy any of them at above 3 <abbr>s</abbr> at moſt, in the Pound Profit, on Pain of Forfeiture of thrice the value to the party grieved or oppreſſed; and if thoſe who have extorted before, of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, out of their Tickets, above 4 <abbr>s</abbr> or at moſt, 5 <abbr>s</abbr> in the Pound Profit, might Pay to the Party grieved and oppreſſed 2<abbr>s</abbr> back for every ſhilling more profit; and that would not be ſo great a puniſhment as ſome may imagine; For if they extorted 10 <abbr>s</abbr> profit, and five being for time paſt winked at, the other five paid back double, is but 10 <abbr>s</abbr> So that the poor extorted ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined Seaman, would have but 20 <abbr>s</abbr> at laſt for 20 <abbr>s</abbr> And if any ſay, there was no Law againſt theſe Extortioning Villains for time paſt: To that I anſwer, I do ſuppoſe, unleſs the Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners are worſe than Heathens, there is the Law of Nature and of Chriſt, to do as they would be done unto.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly.</hi> unleſs thoſe Extortioners are worſe than <hi>Turks,</hi> I have been often informed, that the <hi>Turks</hi> will ſeverely correct a <hi>Jew</hi> if he takes more than a moderate profit of a Chriſtian; they will beat the <hi>Jew</hi> ſeverely. And I do ſuppoſe that ſuch dreadful curſed wretched Extortioners, as have bought ſome Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Pay at near a quarter of the value, were never heard of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Indians,</hi> or the moſt Savage and Barbarous Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the World; And thoſe very Seamen who are ſo Ruined, to loſe their Health and Lives in the defence of that very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where theſe Extortioners muſt live, or be Slaves themſelves, and loſe all at laſt.</p>
            <p>And I conſider, That if <hi>David</hi> would not drink of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> when the Three Mighty Men had ventured their Lives to fetch it, but ſaid, <hi>God forbid: is it not their Blood?</hi> Then how can theſe Nations expect to thrive, that put by the poor miſerable Seamens Widows from their Pay; that was earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55757:10"/>not only with the peril of their Husband's Lives, but even fell ſick, and actually die on ſhore by reaſon thereof; or whether it be not very like injuſtice, or unmercifulneſs, and Cruelty, to cauſe ſo great multitudes to be deprived of their Pay, who have not been one Day or Month hardly out of the Service for ſeveral Years, as by the Ship's Books will appear, except by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or death, that can be proved; and if thoſe, who have help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to throw more miſery on them, be the only men that are in this Nation to Relieve them; the Lord, for Chrift's ſake, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all Landmen from falling into ſuch Diſtreſs; for if Chriſt ſhould ſay to theſe Nations in Judgment, <hi>The ſame meaſure you mete, ſhall be meaſured to you again,</hi> it would be ſad; but what he will do is known only to himſelf; and what his good will and pleaſure is to ſtir me up to write this, he only knoweth.</p>
            <p>And 8thly, Therefore there ought to be care taken what Seamen muſt do for time to come, if they are ſet ſick on ſhore, and the Ships go away before they are well to ſecure their Pay; for I would appeal to all mankind, that hath Grace or Reaſon, yea, or Common Sence, whether it can be thought, that when there is ſeveral ſick Men in Ships, and they ſet on Shoar, ſome in one Port, and ſome in another; Whether the Ships muſt wait until they are well, and how the ſame Men can get to their own Ships again when they are gone? And if they continue ſick or die, or go on board of other Ships, or be ſent to the Hoſpitals, and Run out of their Pay; whether this be not Injuſtice, Cruelty, Opreſſion, Diſcouragement to the King's Service, and that whereby no Man in <hi>England</hi> can be ſafe to Serve his King and Country for time to come; nor no Man ſafe to truſt a Seaman, or Seaman's Wife and Family, one Groat that is in the King's Service on thoſe terms, ſince the Stouteſt Man and Honeſteſt Man in <hi>England,</hi> by keeping long on Board, may fall Sick and Die, or continue Sick, and that a Year or two, and if not go on Board, or be Preſt on board another Ship, and ſo looſe his Pay: I do proteſt in the preſence of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom I Write this, I fear if there be none in theſe Nations to be found to conſider theſe dreadful Caſes, but ſuffer Cruelty and injuſtice to be ſmugled up, that God will Chaſtiſe theſe Nations, until they Learn what it is to Ruin Men and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in their Lives or Pay, thouſands and ten thouſands, as by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55757:10"/>the King's Pay-books and Muſter-books will appear; and they I appeal to; they are ſuch a Regiſter the Nation never ſaw in the Sea Affairs, and the blame muſt lie ſomewhere; and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome hardened Hearts will ſay the Running them out of their Pay, is right enough; but it may be they will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that their turning from Ship to Ship, until Sickneſs or Death came, was the Cauſe of a great part, and I hope they will not be ſo Caſe-hardened as to ſay they were ſerved well enough to be Run out of their Lives, ſo many ten thouſands; alſo I remember the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, in ſome former times, was mighty induſtrious to find out, and Puniſh the Inſtruments that Ruined the King's Liege-People in their Lives and Eſtates; and had we had but the tenth part of Landmen's Poor Families Stripped of all they had in the World, as there hath been Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtripped of their Pay, it would have made a dreadful out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry in <hi>England:</hi> And indeed if our Poor in <hi>England</hi> had been forc'd to be turned from Maſter to Maſter, without a Penny of Mony for ſome Years, as many Seamen have from Ship to Ship, and their miſerable Wives and Children Live on Credit, or Starve; and if at laſt they ſhould, under the burden of all by diſcouragements, fall ſick, and be Run out of their Mony, they had worked for ſeveral Years, as many have been out of their Pay in ſeveral Ships; it would look dreadfully bad. And ſome well-meaning men would have nothing ſaid of it to acquaint the Government, for fear our Enemies ſhould know it; as if the <hi>French,</hi> who hath taken ſo many hundred Ships from us, and near twenty thouſand Men Captive, this War, and hath ſo many Spies, and Treacherous Villains here, and doth, to outward appearance, know a great deal better where to meet our <hi>India</hi> Ships, and <hi>Berbado's</hi> Ships, in ſeveral places to take them Home to <hi>France,</hi> than ours did to ſend Convoys to take them Home to <hi>England;</hi> and yet ſome ſeeming Honeſt Men are afraid the <hi>French,</hi> that take our Ships and Men, ſhould know our Caſe, and in ſhort, I fear he knows it a great deal more exactly than ſome do, or will do in <hi>England,</hi> for I do think ſome in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſeem to do, like what is ſaid of the Woodcocks, to hide their Heads in a Buſh, and think none can ſee them; and ſo if they let the King, Country and Seamen be all Cheated, it will continue to be all ſmuggled up; but my Pen runs thirteen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55757:11"/>to the Dozen, and yet the knavery of the Bakers is ſuch, that if care be not taken, I am afraid ſome of our Seamens Families will be ready to ſtarve: but to that, I ſhould propoſe a Remedy, that Seamen may not be Cheated of their Health, Lives and Pay altogether.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if as many as is poſſible, might be Paid off every year, and that, it may be, would ſave moſt of their Lives, moſt of their Healths, and all their Pay beſides, and we might have Ships enough for a Winter Squadron beſides; and if any did fall Sick, then if the Ship goeth away and leaves him ſet on ſhoar, then if he cannot come on Board to ſet him in the Ships Book diſ-ſick at ſuch a place and time, and the Man, if well to go on Board another Man of War, and to have the Captain of the Man of War ſend up a Certificate to the Office, That ſuch a man that was in ſuch a Ship, is now in his Ship, and this to be Entered in the other Ships Book in the Office to ſave the Poor Seamens Pay; and if the other Ships Book be not there, to have a Regiſter Book to enter it in the mean time; and if the Man continues Sick or Dies, the Surgeon of the place, he is ſent to, to be Bound to give a Certificate of his Caſe to ſave his Pay, ſince it muſt needs ſeem to me to be a barbarous thing towards any, for time paſt, to be turn'd from Ship to Ship, for ſeveral Years; until they fall ſick and die, and then be Run out of their Pay; and it may be their poor Ruined Wives, who hardly have ſeen their Husbands this War, it may be they muſt come 100 or 200 Miles, to ſhew cauſe why they muſt have any mony, and why their Husbands went not on Board their own Ships again; and it may be the Ships Journal, if looked into at the Office, would ſhew the Ship went away in 24 hours: And if <hi>God will bring every work to Judgment,</hi> I doubt our Ships Books and Ships Journals will be ſad Witneſſes againſt the Cruelty of ſome in thoſe Offices, to Run poor Wretches out of their Pay, that the men are, as the Sentence is againſt thoſe that are to be hanged, <hi>Dead, Dead, Dead.</hi> And therefore if I find not any Remedy againſt Ruining the Fatherleſs and the Widow, I will not expect any great Security of our Ships and Merchandiſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo much to that: God is a Jealous God: If we Ruin the Poor of Thirty Thouſand Pounds the Year, by ſome ſort of Tools, and God ſuffers the Nation to loſe ſo many Hundred
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55757:11"/>Thouſand Pounds in Riches, and the King his Cuſtom, by the Ignorance, Careleſsneſs, and Treachery of others; if our own Folly be not too hard for us, I fear the Judgments of God will: and therefore I adviſe ſome way for theſe Nations to break off their ſins by Repentance, and their Iniquities, by ſhewing mercy to the Poor: and Mercy and Juſtice both, will teach ways to ſecure Ruined Seamens Pay, when wounded, or dead, or in the Hoſpitals.</p>
            <p>9. It is a miſerable thing, that when men are turn'd over, or dead, or ſick, that their poor Wives cannot be informed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their poor Ruined Husbands are Run out of their Pay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Petitioning; Which, if there be Twenty Thouſand Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings over in a Year, may make work for the Clerk of the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and his Maſters. If they all Petition at 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d</hi>
               </abbr> the Piece to him, it is a Thouſand Pound the Year, and 6<abbr>
                  <hi>d</hi>
               </abbr> to his Boy, is five hundred Pound the Year: And will not this be brave Times for him? But I remember, in all Calamities, ſome dreadful Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches get mony; in the time of the Plague of <hi>London,</hi> in the time of the Fire, and in the time of War, many are Raiſed from the Dunghill on the Ruines of others; but why poor Seamen themſelves, or their poor Wives, ſhould not have Liberty to get a Clerk to ſearch the Book, to ſee if they are cheated of their Pay or no, before Pay-day, is ſad. But I confeſs it is a good way to hide Knavery: For if mony be ſaid to be paid the Party, and was not, and he appears himſelf, it is a timely notice to get an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other book to ſhew him, that it was only ordered to be paid him. But if he be dead, or gone, and never come himſelf, then it may ſtand paid the party until Dooms-day; and if he comes, it was a miſtake: And beſides this, having a ſight of the Books, may be a great help to Extortioners and Ticket-buyers, if they get the Books ſearched privately, they may buy as they pleaſe; And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not <hi>turning the blind out of their way,</hi> ſeeing the Seamens Wives have moſt time nothing but the Books to know what is due; and if they be Run at Pay-day, it may be are forced to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and ſtay for their mony another year; and this is miſery to miſery.</p>
            <p>10. Therefore I think they ought, for time to come, to have no Seamen diſcharged without a Ticket, and no Officer keep his Ticket on pain of Felony; For in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is worſt,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55757:12"/>a Pick-pocket ſtealing a Guinea or Two from a Gentleman, or a Captain of a Man of War to take a Seaman's Ticket from him of Ten Pound, and it may be the poor Seaman, nor his Wife and Family, hath not a Groat in the World to buy a bit of bread? Therefore if there be not Relief to poor Ruined Seamen, I will never more wonder we fool away, knock on the Head, betray and deſtroy ſo many Men of War and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Ships. But,</p>
            <p>11. And none to wait above One Payment for One Ticket alſo, for time to come; and not wait 3 years for 30 <abbr>s</abbr> at Two Payments of a Ticket, as hath been common this War: And whether this was not Miſery to Miſery? And to prevent that,</p>
            <p>12. As few as poſſible to be turn'd from Ship to Ship; but when Ships come in, pay them off as they come in, ſome one time, and ſome another; and the Men have a Month's Liberty to come on ſhore; and gather health and ſtrength, and ſpend their Mony; and when their Mony is gone, their Friends will quickly ſend them to Sea again, without preſſing; and that would be good for King and Country: And if Men ſee they are not ſhifted from Ship to Ship, like Slaves, they will, when paid off on ſhore, as in other Ages, have Encouragement to come into the Service again, and bring their Children, Servants and Friends with them. But if they find they are deprived of their Liberty all their Days, when once they come, and of their Property, when ſick and die, no marvel if they are glad to get away: And I would ask all Mankind, and would appeal to the King and Parliament what ſhould be the Cauſe the King's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice now ſhould be more a Priſon than in other Ages? and why ſo Gracious a King's Service ſhould be made ſuch a Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear now; and ſuch Loſs of Liberty, Property and Lives to the Seamen now more than in any Age of the World; and whether it be not an unmerciful, unjuſt, and an unreaſonable Argument to pretend the Seamen cannot be admitted to come on ſhore to be paid now, as in other Ages, becauſe they will Run away: Whereas, in the mean time, they are kept turn'd and toſſed from Ship to Ship, until more die than would Man the Fleet; and in the mean time alſo, more Run away from the Service than would Man it all and half over again: And if they are Run out of their Pay wrongfully, it is ſhameful and cruel; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55757:12"/>if Juſtly, their New Management has frightned more Seamen out of the Service, to the appearance of the Ship's Books, this Seven Years laſt, than hath Run away in this Nation, I do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſuppoſe, this fifty years, if all the Old Books and New Books were ſearched. So that I ſay, Experience ſhews the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of that Argument of paying them on board Ship, by the Loſs of near Forty Thouſand Lives, and ſixty or ſeventy Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men's Pay: Whereas, had their Lives been preſerved, and their Pay encouraged on ſhore, in all likelihood Seamen would have been ſo increaſed, and thereby their Pay in Merchant Ships near half Ieſs: That conſidering the hazard of Loſt Voyages in Merchant Ships, they would there have Thouſands of them proved my Words good, that I uſed to ſay to them at firſt, That the King's Service was the beſt in <hi>England;</hi> No half Pay, no Dammage, no Loſt Voyage; and if pinched of their Diet, the King pays the Pinch-gut-mony alſo honeſtly.</p>
            <p>And thus <hi>I</hi> would by the way conſider, that we cannot expect to be in ſafety for time to come, without we do by Humility, Juſtice and Mercy, engage God to ſtand by us, and give us Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and his Bleſſing in the firſt place.</p>
            <p>And 2dly, As to outward means, in a viſible way, we cannot be ſafe and happy in times of Peace or War, without an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Thouſand Seamen in <hi>England.</hi> My Reaſon is this, That tho now we have the <hi>Dutch</hi> united with us, and it may be ſave 20 or 30 Ships, and 10000 Men, the time may fall out we may ſtand alone; and 2dly, What hath been, may be; and the <hi>French</hi> and another Nation have Joyned againſt us; and then we need double the Strength and Number of Men we have now; and that to maintain a War and Merchant Trade both; and if we do not that we are Ruined for want of Trade; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this I would ſay, Tho our Loſſes have been dreadful this War, and God knows, many of them blindfold, and ſcandalous and ignorant; yet it was a great mercy we traded; Our poor had been Ruined, if we had not Traded; all our Manufactory-workers would have been ready to periſh, and commit, it may be, any miſchief; for it hath been with the Nation as it may be, in ſome part, with my ſelf; There are ſome that have by the Providence of God a Subſiſtence from me; I trade, and truſt, and loſe much; I pay them, bleſſed be God, they live by their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55757:13"/>Labour, and ſome might ſtarve, if they had not that, or the Pariſhes muſt keep them; others, it may be, get Mony, more than I, under me, becauſe I ſtand to all hazards, and they to none, but take my Mony. So it is in a Nation; if we had not Traded this War, we had been Ruined; and if we loſe not more than we get clear Profit, we ſhall live at laſt; tho, by the way, the World may admire at us, that have near twice the Number of Men of War imploy'd that the <hi>Dutch</hi> have, and yet that they ſhould have ſo many Millions of Riches come home from the <hi>Indies,</hi> and other parts, this year, and other years, and hardly loſe any almoſt to ſpeak of, except what they have loſt in our Company; for where they take care of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns themſelves, for the moſt part they go and come well. But in concluſion, I do ſuppoſe, beſides their preſervation of their Shipping, if I am not under a miſapprehenſion, they ſave a Million of Mony a year more than we in their Ships of War, and Mens Wages, and it may be half a Million more in the very Wages of Seamen in their Merchants Service; and if they ſpend leſs by half, and loſe leſs by Eight Parts in Ten, they will out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do us in Trade; and it is not our making a Noiſe, and keeping our Seamen on Board of Ship until they die, will ſave our Trade alive; but firſt the bleſſing of God; 2. The increaſe and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of our Seamen, and our preſerving them alive; and having enough to ſupply the Merchant-men with Seamen cheap, and then having Men to order our Convoys, at leaſt with as much common ſenſe to preſerve our Merchant Ships, and meet them as ſoon, and take them home to <hi>England,</hi> for time to come, as the <hi>French</hi> uſe to do; to meet them to take them home to <hi>France,</hi> that we may not be a Grief to our Friends, and a Joy to our Enemies, and a by-word to the World. I bleſs God I love my Native Country well, and our gracious King <hi>William</hi> well; and if I did not, I would not be ſo plain hearted. And as to what I ſaid before, we muſt, for time to come, imploy at leaſt half as many Seamen more in times of Peace, than ever we did; and to do it in time of Peace, if we would, when ever God in Mercy ſends us peace; then mind the very Fiſhing Trade at our own Doors, as others do. I find it computed by one Sir <hi>John Burrows,</hi> Keeper of the Records in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and printed with <hi>Gerard Malines Lex Mercatoriae,</hi> which I have by me, That
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55757:13"/>the <hi>Dutch</hi> do imploy in our <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Sea, which he ſaith is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Harveſt, and doth imploy 6400 Ships and Buſſes, and 120000 Men at Sea; whereby he ſaith, That <hi>Holland</hi> it ſelf being but 28 Miles in length, and a few in breadth, imploys in all their Sea-Trade 10000 Sail of Shipping; and he ſaith, That <hi>Lubeck</hi> hath 700 Sail of Ships, <hi>Hamborough</hi> 600, <hi>Emden</hi> more, beſides Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and other Nations that Fiſh and Trade in our Seas: And he ſaith, That the very Cuſtoms of their Fiſhing Trade of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> came to 500000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> the Year, including the Tenth Fiſh, and Cask paid for Waftage. And this, if thought of by <hi>England,</hi> when ever God ſhall ſend Peace, would be the way to imploy and increaſe our Seamen, and to have a ſufficient Number always ready to ſerve the King and Country at 2 Months Warning; and not ſuffer our Seamen, in Peace, to rove all over the world for imployment to get bread, yea to go ſome Thouſands into the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> a Buckaneering, for want of bread at home. This is by the way. It may be ſomething of this may be minded ſome Years hence. And this I would leave as a <hi>Memorandum,</hi> That ſince <hi>France</hi> is grown ſo prodigious Great, if we double not our Diligence, they will endeavour to out-wit us in Peace or War: and it may be they may be to <hi>England</hi> as the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when we fall deeply to ſinning, they may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up to ſcourge us; and the Lord prevent the Cauſe, and if it be his holy Will, enable us to bring them under.</p>
            <p>11. And I would ſay, That all poſſible care ought to be taken, that thoſe, who have the Command and Offices in the Ships of War, ſhould be Men of true Courage in fight, and true Kindneſs to the Seamen at other times: And I would appeal to all our Brave Commanders, if the Seamen, with good uſage, will not be led with a twined Thread, up to the Muzzels of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Guns, at any time, by Stout, good Natur'd Commanders: But hate to be abuſed like Dogs. And I am conſulting my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and do not remember any one Commander that was an Hectoring, and Swearing, Damning, Cruel Wretch to his Men, that ever had the Heart to fight an Enemy: And therefore it were in this Age well, if there were a Law made. <hi>Tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Correction ſhould be given to Seamen in Paſſion; but to have Three, or at leaſt Two Officers adviſe in any Correction more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55757:14"/>
            <p>12. That no Seaman be kept above 2 Years out, either in the <hi>Straits</hi> or <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> before they come home, and be paid off; it having been often found, Ships ſtaying long there, have had their Number of Men 6 times over, to the Seamen's Ruin. And <hi>I</hi> never heard of a Penny Profit to King and Country, by their Ruining of ſo many.</p>
            <p>13. None be ſo turned over above once before his firſt mony be paid, and that to prevent the Ruin of their Pay and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
            <p>14. None to forfeit a Penny of the other Ship's Pay, after he is 3 Months in the Ship.</p>
            <p>15. No Officer to detain a Seaman's Ticket on any pretence whatever, except his Covenant-Servant, on pain of Felony.</p>
            <p>16. None to ſet a <hi>Q.</hi> or <hi>R.</hi> on any Seaman's Pay, but to ſhew Cauſe, and ſet his Name that did it, that Seamen may not be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Life, and Death and Pay and All, by they know not who, nor wherefore.</p>
            <p>17. None to receive a Seaman's Pay without a true Power; and if Counterfeited, to have the Middle Joint of each Little Finger cut off, and be ſold to the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> for perpetual Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude all their Days.</p>
            <p>18. No Officer to detain a Seaman's Certificate, or Sick-Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, on any pretence whatever.</p>
            <p>19. No Officer to keep Men open on the Books a Voyage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are gone, neither to make out Tickets for them, or to enter Men in the Ship's Books, that never ſaw the Ship in their Lives. And to prevent this and the other, and the Cheating the King; and Loſs of Ships, and Ruin of Seamen for time to come, there might be,</p>
            <p>20. One man in 20 that can write and Caſt Accompt, to be as Seamen <hi>extra,</hi> to keep a Journal ſign'd by them all, of the daily motion of the Ship, in what place, what Wind, and what Friends or Enemies met with, or run away from; and alſo to take an Exact Account of all the Ship's Victuals and Stores coming on Beard, to ſee that it is the full Quantity, and that no Embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be in the Stores, nor no Victuals ſhort, ſince the King allows enough of all theſe things, if men ſhuffle it not away; and alſo to ſee the men muſtered every week all the Voyage on board, to prevent their being entred that never come on board; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55757:14"/>they kept open that Run away: And that alſo the Seamen <hi>extra</hi> might be Learning to carry a Ship to Sea in any part of the World, and conſulted with in caſe of Danger, that Ships might not be knockt on the head, or fool'd away, for time to come, ſo madly as in ſome times paſt; and theſe men to have ſix ſhillings the Month more than Able Seamen; and to be preferr'd, if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving.</p>
            <p>21. In regard that the Boatſwains, Gunners and Carpenters are Places of great Care and Truſt, and ſome Expences in the getting in, and taking care of, and accounting for their Stores, and their Wages being, it may be, under-valued, in reſpect of thoſe who have double Pay, if his Majeſty, and the Honourable Houſes, would advance their Pay half as much more as they have now, and this would be the way to encourage them to be honeſt, faithful and cheery in the Service; and they that are not honeſt, to be puniſhed: if they are found to ſteal the King's Store, then they and the Parties who are the Receivers, which are as bad as the Thieves, to be every man that is found guilty, marked on the Little Fingers, and tranſported for Servants to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> all their Days, as thoſe that would infect others if they ſtaid here: And to find out all Theft, if there were this Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That whatever Seamen 2 or 3 could prove the ſame, to have their diſcharge from the Ship, on the Conviction of the Offender, and Tickets for their own mony, to be paid preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the <hi>Pay-Office,</hi> and a Protection for One Year from the Preſs, except they can be preferr'd in the time to ſome place, into ſome other Ship. And this would be the way to have almoſt all the Thieves in the Fleet, and in the Yards diſcovered, and without Charge or Loſs to the King. But if men who diſcover Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be abuſed, brow-beaten and back-beaten, and confin'd to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it all their days, no marvel if there is ſeldom any Thievery found out, if never ſo much committed.</p>
            <p>22. No Purſers, or Captains Clerks, or any Officers, to give a Liſt of Names to others, to forge Powers, or to deliver out Tickets to any, but publickly; and to thoſe who have Powers, that are Lawful to take the ſame; and none to ſell or receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Seaman's Pay or Ticket, except their own Indenture-Serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, on Pain of Felony, as being worſe than Highway-men.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55757:15"/>
            <p>23. There to be a Committee to hear the Complaints of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe who have been oppreſſed, cheated, or ruined in their Pay; and to hear all Complaints freely, and to reſtore Juſtice to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as thoſe who would not have the hand of God go out againſt our Navigation any more, to the ſuffering either our own Folly or the Enemies Subtilty to ruin us.</p>
            <p>24. That whenever Ships are put up for Re-calls at <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> for Pay, there be a certain time appointed for each Ship, and publick notice given at leaſt 6 days before-hand, for all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to appear, that have Mony due, that they may not loſe their Pay, or come at ſuch uncertainties for ſmall ſums, that the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and charge, and loſs of time, is worth more than the Mony receiv'd.</p>
            <p>25. That there may be alſo an appointment of ſome of the Commiſſioners, that ſtate the publick Accounts, to hear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all Informations, wherein the King and Nation have been cheated, and liberty to grant a ſafe Conduct to any one to come and appear before them, to make a full and free diſcovery, and to let them depart home without moleſtation again; and if their Information be worthy of a Pardon, that it might be interceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; if not, that they might be left open to the Law, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And that, if any one, that hath been guilty of Cheating, and forging of Powers, can diſcover two others as bad as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo as they may be convicted, then the firſt to be pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the other two puniſhed: And if the other two can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them diſcover two more, that is four as bad as themſelves, the two to be excuſed, and the four corrected, unleſs any of them could double their Information, as aforeſaid; and this would be one way, perhaps, to find out how the King, and the Nation, and the Seamen may be modeſtly Judged to be cheated of 100 or 150000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> a year this War.</p>
            <p>And now I having propoſed this, it may be I ſhall meet with ſome Enemies that will envy me ten times worſe than the Thieves envied him that wrote the Book that is called, <hi>The Engliſh Rogue;</hi> and yet if they were ſo wiſe, as to keep their own Counſel, none would know I meant them; for indeed, I bleſs God I aim not againſt perſons, but Villany; and if I meet with any that is offended at me for diſcovering the Method of the Navy-Cheats, I ſhall think it is ſome body that is galled and ſcabbed; and that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55757:15"/>I touched them, tho I did not ſee them, and therefore they kick and bite, as ſome Horſes will do. And ſo much to that. I would adviſe them to keep their own Counſel, that others may not laugh at them; and if they laugh themſelves, and are pleaſed, the World will be ready to judge they are glad if I can hunt out the Scabby Sheep out of their Flock. But I would propoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe many thouſands that are taken captive into <hi>France,</hi> if it were in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships.</p>
            <p>26. That they that are taken may have their ſeveral miſeries conſidered of, how they are uſed in <hi>France;</hi> and if their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be ſo great, that they are ready to periſh there for want, it would be well if ſome Relief were ordered them, that they might not die, and periſh there, or be forced to enter into the <hi>French</hi> Service for Liberty, Bread and Cloaths, and therefore to be ſent for away, alſo ſo ſoon as poſſible they can conveniently.</p>
            <p>27. When come to <hi>Plimouth,</hi> or any Sea-Port Town in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to have at leaſt a penny a mile allowed every Seaman for Travelling Charges to <hi>London,</hi> if in Men of War, and to where their Friends live, if in Merchant Ships, that they may not be forc'd to beg or ſtarve for near 200 miles, and at laſt be forc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into other Ships, without one penny of mony to buy them Clothes for to ſhift them: And it may be conſidered, if it be not a barbarous thing to meet men as far as <hi>Kingſton,</hi> coming home out of <hi>France,</hi> with nothing but their Louſie Old Cloaths the <hi>French</hi> give them, and when they have begged 150 miles, to carry them away, lay them in the Hold in Preſs-Ketches, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bedding, or any thing to lie under or over them; and it may be the poor Wretches ſickly and weak, ſome of them: And this is now at this time one Fruit of our keeping Seamen on board, and paying them there, that they ſhould not Run away, until there is ſo many dead and gone, that there is dreadful Tearing ann Halling in City and Country, and the very Watermen out of the Tiltboats, that they are afraid to work on their Trades, ſome of them now, while our great Ships are ſo many laid up: And by the way, this preſſing, when Men were paid lately, frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away ſome Hundreds or Thouſands of Seamen: Whereas if they had but had <hi>liberty</hi> to have ſpent their <hi>mony freely</hi> in one month, they would have been glad to have gone again. I have heard a Friend of mine declare <hi>ſolemnly,</hi> He had above 20 Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55757:16"/>that belonged to his Houſe, went <hi>away</hi> to their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, not daring to come up to <hi>London</hi> to ſpend their <hi>money here,</hi> or return it home to their Friends; and if <hi>ſo many be ſeared away</hi> in one houſe, <hi>how many</hi> in all the houſes that keep Lodgers in <hi>City and Suburbs?</hi> Therefore men muſt be taken care of for time to come, to have their Lives preſerved, and their perſons encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; or if not, I fear it will produce greater Loſs and Damage than is yet foreſeen; And all mankind that knows the Sea-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; knows that 2 or 3 Years keeping on board of Ship, <hi>common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 3 fourths of the men die: whereas if <hi>they had liberty,</hi> and freſh proviſions, and Land-Air, one month often recruits them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>28. Therefore the Seamen to be encouraged, and preſerved, and paid off at <hi>London,</hi> as <hi>formerly,</hi> and the <hi>City</hi> would not be Ruined by the War. And if it be objected, <hi>The Seamen would then go in Merchant-Ships, many of them.</hi> To that I do anſwer, if their Lives were preſerved, they would increaſe as faſt or faſter in Men of War than in Merchant-Ships: and if there were <hi>plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Wages would fall in Merchant-Ships. And had our Fleet increaſed Seamen, as it was expected, the Wages would have been ſo low in Merchant-Ships, and what with <hi>Loſt Voyages,</hi> Seamen would have ſtrived to have gone into the King's Ships, if they had been paid off in <hi>every Ship,</hi> and had <hi>Liberty.</hi> But when they have no hopes of Releaſe, but Death, or the End of the War, and cannot <hi>have opportunity</hi> to fight to end the War, this is <hi>a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Caſe:</hi> many of them have complained they wanted to fight it out for to end the War. And,</p>
            <p>29. This paying the Seamen off on Shore yearly, that is, one half one Year, and another half another Year, would many times ſave the King near as much charge in ſmall Ships Victuals and Wages, while as our Ship is in the Dock, as the charge of mending the Ship comes to. And indeed this War hath been, it may be, ſuch a Diſappointment to Seamen, as the World ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew, ſome Commanders having had ſo much Love and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and Care, as to have Men to Man a Ship; and it may be in ſome months after, either the men turn'd great part into other Ships, or the Commanders removed into other Ships; ſo that if a Thouſand Seamen would be freely willing to ſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch brave Commanders, as I know ſome, they are not ſure,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55757:16"/>but in a month they may exchange their Drivers. And by the way, I would obſerve, That tho the Double-Pay Officers have had Pay ſuitable to buy Two Canes to beat the poor Seamen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of one; whereas before, they ſometimes did tie a Rope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarn at the end of their Cleft Sticks, but now may buy new; but the poor Seamen had not 1 <abbr>s</abbr> the month more all this War, to buy one courſe Coat or Waſtcoat to keep off a blow. Which brings me to another Paragraph, that is,</p>
            <p>30. That the poor Seamen may have their 40 <abbr>s</abbr> a piece for Cloaths, uſed to be allowed them if the Ship was loſt; and this they had before they beat the <hi>French;</hi> and before that, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſome Comforts now and then. But to go on,</p>
            <p>31. No Seamen to be forced to go out of a Man of War in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Merchant-Ship, altho the Captain ſhould have ſeveral pounds for the ſame. But if Neceſſity requires the Lending of a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Two to a Merchant, the Seaman may have all the <hi>Pay</hi> in the Merchant-Ship, and the Captain and Purſer to have the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Victuals only in the Man of War, that the King and the Seamen be not both cheated at one time. And,</p>
            <p>32. The Seaman to have a Certificate to come again in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time, and to be kept from the Preſs until then.</p>
            <p>33. No Seaman to be made wait above ten days at the Navy-Office, to petition for to have a <hi>Q</hi> or <hi>R.</hi> taken off. But if when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever paid-off, as formerly, and incouraged, there would be an end almoſt to that dreadful wretched Ruining and Deſtruction to themſelves and Families, of loſing their mony, for thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters being ſet on by any <hi>wrongfully;</hi> and therefore would ſerve the King cheerfully.</p>
            <p>34. That thoſe, who are diſcharged fair, by Reaſon of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and have Tickets ſigned by all the Officers for their <hi>Pay,</hi> may not be cheated of it, for the word of one hard hearted wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che's pleaſure, the Seamen's Ruin being too great already.</p>
            <p>35. If Seamen are preſt away when on Shore, the Captain that commands the Ship he is in, to be obliged to ſend a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to the Ticket-Office, to be Regiſtred in the other Ship's book, or in a Regiſter-Book, as in the Caſe before of Sickneſs, to ſecure the Seaman's <hi>Pay</hi> from being ruined, becauſe he loſt his Liberty.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:55757:17"/>
            <p>36. That it may be conſidered there are 3 things <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> do value highly, that is, <hi>Liberty, Property and Life,</hi> and all theſe have the Seamen loſt ſome ſhare of this War, and the Hiſtories of all theſe Nations cannot parallel; and therefore double Care ought to be taken of them for time to come, ſeeing it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there is ſome gone to enquire after the preſerving of thoſe things in other Nations already, as by the King's Books of Ships come home this Year, may be ſeen ſomething.</p>
            <p>37. Seamen preſſed out of Merchant-Ships, to be under the penalty of half their <hi>Pay,</hi> to go on board of ſuch a Man of War, at ſuch a time, and then to have liberty to bring up the <hi>Merchant-Ship,</hi> and to take half their <hi>Pay,</hi> and ſell their Ventures, and recruit themſelves a few <hi>days,</hi> to recover their health, that they may not, after long Voyages, infect the men of War by ſickneſs; and when they are gone on board, that man of War to have a Certificate ſent up to the Office, <hi>That ſuch a man is come on board ſuch a Man of War;</hi> and then his other half of his <hi>Pay</hi> to be paid to his Attorney: And if he goeth not on board the <hi>Man of War,</hi> or if ſhe be ordered away ſooner, than on board another; then the other half of his <hi>Pay</hi> to be forfeit to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital of <hi>Greenwich,</hi> if he goeth not in <hi>a Man of War.</hi> And by this means moſt of the Seamen might be in the King's Service once in 2 Years, and the others that have been there diſcharged, and paid off, would pleaſe the Seamen, increaſe them, ſave their Lives and Pay. And if ſo, there might be a Law made, to cauſe all <hi>Maſters</hi> to regiſter them that come home for the King's uſe, before they are paid, and all other Regiſters will be too ſhort, there being, it may be, 40000 Seamen Batchelors, or ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found to be regiſtred, but lodge 40 or 50 in a houſe; and if regiſtred there, can be gone 100 miles next week. But good Pay, their Lives preſerved, and good loving Commnaders, that will fight with their Enemies, and be as kind to the Seamen as Lambs, would ſet almoſt all to Rights again in a Year or Two, if they be not ruined at the new way of management in the Offices afterward.</p>
            <p>38. And therefore they that are ſent to the Hoſpitals, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a Year or 2 ſick, muſt not be cheated out of their pay, or have that barbarous word told to a periſhing Wife, <hi>That her Husband ſhould not have been ſick;</hi> when if he had been ſick two Years, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55757:17"/>before quite well, crawled into a <hi>Man of War again,</hi> and there continued, might deſerve, more eſpecially if the Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have Relief of the Pariſhes, and the man ſtill in the Service alſo.</p>
            <p>And indeed I find our Poor's Book in the Suburbs, below the <hi>Tower,</hi> ſmell very ſtrong of the Ruin of the Seamen's Families; our Taxes for the Poor being doubled: And it may be ſome that would grudg to give a poor ruined Seaman's Family 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>d</hi>
               </abbr> to buy them bread, if they were ready to ſtarve, may yet blame me for troubling my head with their Caſes, and Ruins, and miſeries: but however, my Conſcience beareth me Witneſs, that I ſerve God and King <hi>William,</hi> and the good Old <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Intereſt, in what I do: And ſo long as I have ſweet peace within, I cannot ſo much as <hi>fear any thing of trouble can hurt me;</hi> for, I bleſs God, <hi>I</hi> have <hi>learned in part, as a Chriſtian, to be content with what God allotteth me;</hi> And <hi>I</hi> have <hi>alſo learn'd</hi> this Principle, <hi>That an honeſt man is not ſubject to injury; a man may kill him, but cannot hurt him.</hi> And now <hi>I</hi> ſpeak of that, makes me think of ſome that threatned to ſacrifice me laſt Year; and when the News was brought my dear Wife, ſhe was frighted: But I bleſs God I feared it not: For as God carrieth me on, that I cannot let the Ruin, and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Cruelty, and Injuſtice, that is exerciſed on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seamen, more than ever the World ſaw, to be hid from the King and Parliament; ſo by the Grace of God, he carrieth me above fear of any ſufferings, ſo long as I have Truth on my ſide, and thoſe Two Graces of my ſide, Juſtice and Mercy, that will bear me up. But if all the Reaſon and Underſtanding I have left, do not fail me, I have all the common Policy of my ſide that can be imagined. And now I ſpeak to that, I will be plain hearted and declare my Opinion, That I do verily think, if there were no Policy on my ſide, that if the Seamen were oppreſſed and ruined, they and their Families, as multitudes have been, the Juſtice of God would awake againſt the Nation.</p>
            <p>And 2. I do alſo verily judge if there were no provoking E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in their Ruin, they are ruined ſo madly, and dead, and run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſo ſhamefully, that it would be the way to ſpoil our ſelves at laſt, if it proceeds much farther; for their Ruin doth increaſe the pretence of keeping them turn'd from Ship to Ship, or catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them next day, or the ſame they are paid: And if there be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55757:18"/>not liberty of freſh Air and freſh Proviſions, Experience ſhews the ſalt Seas and ſalt Victuals, in ſtaying long in Ships, kills ten times more than the Sword: And God forbid, that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould bave cauſe to rejoice, and ſay, as long as this War laſts, he need not fight to kill our men; for they die faſter without his fighting. And in ſhort, if this War had been a Game at Cards, I ſhould have feared ſome Gameſters plaid booty; if it had been a Suit of Law, I ſhould have verily Judged there were ſome took double Fees. But my wandring, roving Brains do rather think our Sea-Affairs look more like that Rude Play, call'd, <hi>Blind man's Buff;</hi> for we have had ſeveral ſcurvy hard blows, that we could not well tell who it was that did hit us: But however it is, my Wiſdom is too ſmall to unriddle the whole, altho I have Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſecret Notions that at preſent ſerve for my own inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And this that I write is ſomething that bubbles over; And if any ſhould go farther, and ſay, <hi>Whatever the Game was, ſome that were either to hold or decide ſome of the Stakes, have gotten great Eſtates, let as many Gameſters as will, be ruined.</hi> Now that I would leave to thoſe, who have more skill to determine. I am almoſt aſhamed of this rambling diſcourſe, and will now ſay what comes next to hand; and that is, That we had need to ſecure our Walls; and if the Seamen are call'd our Walls, they had need to be repaired all that is poſſible; And if any ſay, Great part of them are new ones, and ſo ſhould laſt well; To that I anſwer, it may fall out the newer they are, the more apt to fall; whereas thoſe which are old and ſeaſoned, if preſerved any thing like, would do better: And to that I might ſay, Perhaps it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; for in <hi>England</hi> we need never want men for the Sea; but Seamen are men ſeaſoned to the Sea. And by the way I would obſerve, That our brave Seamen that have been 7 Years in the Service, they never had a penny Bounty-mony in the Spring; it is they that come in afterwards get Bounty-mony: And I have wondred, thoſe that managed the Seamen did not think of ſome incouragement for thoſe who ſtood all the time, as well as for thoſe who come in the laſt week. It is an old ſaying in <hi>England, The Eye of the Maſter makes the Horſe fat;</hi> And indeed, if our moſt gracious King <hi>William</hi> had been Rightly informed, to have ſeen the Caſe of his Loyal Seamen, they would have been in better plight. And this brings me to conſider, That the Victualling of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55757:18"/>our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navy, is the beſt in the World; that is allowed them, if they have what the King allows: And therefore,</p>
            <p>39. It were well for the Seamen, if the Purſers were bound, and made to take all the Sea-ſtores on board of Ship, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to receive any ſhort at the Office at firſt, neither to ſell any away before they come as far as my Houſe, and that is not a mile from the Victualling-Office; and then Ships need not go to ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowance often in 14 days after they are at Sea; and if that were prevented, it were well. But it may be they may plead, They can anſwer it, becauſe if they are found out, they muſt pay for it: Now to that I would ſay, it is well for all the Nobility's, and Gentry's, and Yeomen's Horſes in <hi>England,</hi> that they have not Purſers to feed them; that if their Maſters allow them 10 or 20 Quarters of Oats for a Stable, the Grooms, that ſhould feed them, take a third of them, and ſell them, and drink away the mony between the Drivers and the Grooms; and reckon ſo many Pecks a day; and if the Horſes are abroad at work, and come not in time, charge their Oats to the Maſter's Account, tho they are ſold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and they eat none in 2 or 3 days, or a week: And indeed, bad Drivers and bad Feeders is enough to ſpoil any Team of Horſe in the World. I have heard among Countrymen, in <hi>Kent,</hi> ſome ſay, There is half in half difference in driving Cattle; ſome will beat them, and whip them, and knock them over the Pate, and ſwear and damn like Devils at the Cattle, and ſpoil them, that they will hardly drive at all, or it may be break their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and run away, and ſpoil the Team at laſt; whereas, if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that knows how to manage them with care, and cheereth them up, clappeth them on the back with his hand, and chirups lovingly to them, they will draw like Lions. And in ſhort, I will appeal to all the Yeomen in <hi>Kent,</hi> many of whom are my Relations, if ever they knew a Team of Horſe get a Groat clear Gains for their Maſters, at 7 Years End, whoſe Drivers and Hoſtlers had ruined them half, and near ſtarved ſome of the reſt, and cheated their Maſters in the mean time of more a great deal than their Provender came to. But I had need intreat par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for my rambling; but ſometimes there may be Abundance of homely Truths ſpoken in Jeſt; <hi>and it may be too true to make a Jeſt of.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55757:19"/>
            <p>But however, now to the Seamen of <hi>England;</hi> They are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as true to the Intereſt of King <hi>William,</hi> to the laſt, as any ſort of men whatever; and many of thoſe, who have ſtood in the King's Books as <hi>Run-aways,</hi> are either dead in his Service, and that is the laſt they can do for him; and others are ſtill in his Service to this hour, tho Run out of their Pay in other Ships; And in ſhort, it looks very miſerable alſo, to be Run out of their Pay in other Ships, and cannot obtain leave once in 3 or 4 Years to come to ſhew Cauſe, or hear Reaſon why they ſhould have their mony. I remember the <hi>Heathen Romans</hi> are ſaid to take <hi>care not to condemn men without being heard ſpeak for themſelves, and alſo ſeeing their Accuſers.</hi> Now if it be objected, that it cannot be expected all that are made Run ſhould ſee their Accuſers, yet for the 2d, they might have this priviledge <hi>Heathens</hi> allowed of, <hi>ſpeaking for themſelves:</hi> And therefore I think in the next place,</p>
            <p>40. It is but Reaſon and Juſtice the Seamen that are made Run, ſhould be protected 14 days, to petition to get off their <hi>R. S.</hi> But I am much afraid that it will be found Cruelty at laſt, to make men loſe their <hi>Pay</hi> that are dead a-ſhore, or ſick in the Hoſpitals, or not a month out of the King's Service theſe ſeveral Years, or diſcharged fair by Tickets ſigned by all the Officers. And this I would ask, <hi>Whether the King's Service be a perpetual bondage?</hi> That tho a man be Really ſick, and have a Ticket given him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him ſick, ſigned by all the Officers, to clear him, and get his <hi>Pay,</hi> whether it be not Oppreſſion and Cruelty in thoſe that ſhould pay the mony, to deprive theſe men of their mony, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they, that they left their Powers with, do not know preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where the man is, or whether living or dead, or in what Ship; and it may be, it is ſome Years paſt ſince he was diſcharged, and whether <hi>this way of management be like to encourage the Seamen, or any that truſt them, or the like?</hi> In plain <hi>Engliſh, Such managers would fright away the Seamen, and fright others from truſting them.</hi> And now I have ſaid this, it may be ſome will think I write this for intereſt, and am concerned with ſuch a Caſe. To that I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, No; for I left off buying 3 Years paſt, and now write on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerve God, and my King and Country; And if I were in another Country, and ſhould hear theſe things, it may be I might be aſhamed of thoſe kind of Actions, and Abundance more, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55757:19"/>I fear are againſt <hi>Law and Goſpel; and Honeſty and Policy,</hi> yea, and I fear againſt good <hi>Heathen Morality;</hi> and ſeems to be <hi>all Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</hi> But now I hope our Gracious King and Loyal Parliament have eſpouſed the <hi>Seamen's Cauſe,</hi> they will, as an honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Houſe of Commons ſaid, endeavour to do them Right. And this ſhort Prayer I will put up for the Seamen for time to come, <hi>That the King and Parliament would not leave them and their Families to the tender mercies of the wicked;</hi> for the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that cannot lie, ſaith, <hi>That the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> And it may be ſome that have been a year a getting a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for Juſtice Anſwered, may underſtand ſomething of the meaning of that, when they come to beg nothing but their own that was due to them, by plain Juſtice, bare and thread-bare, and ſtark naked Juſtice and Honeſty: Therefore if there be not ſome way to ſecure poor Seamen's <hi>Pay</hi> for time to come, it is paſt my skill to warrant our Sea-Port Towns will ſend their Men, Children or Servants into the Service ſo freely as before; and it may be they that have been ſo ſerved, as aforeſaid, if they are not dead, yet will not come without good words. And,</p>
            <p>41. Therefore if I might humbly preſume to give my thought, I would ſuppoſe it requiſite not only to <hi>take all care imaginable to ſecure the Seamen's Lives, and Pay, and Health, but alſo to have the Act for their Encouragement read in every Ship once a quarter, and an Abſtract of the Encouragement ſet up in the Sea-Port Towns of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>or at leaſt the Heads of it put in the</hi> Gazette, <hi>that the Nation may ſee, for time to come, that they do not pay their many, and the Seamen ruined; but that the Seamen ſhall be encouraged, and alſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly paid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>42. That they might be paid in <hi>London,</hi> that the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that is always ready to aſſiſt his Majeſty with money, may have ſome again from the Seamen; and not let thoſe who <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> the Seamen, put the King to extraordinary charge to pay the Seamen ſeveral miles off, to the depriving the City of their Trade, and the ſpoiling of near half the Seamens Pay beſides; For in ſhort, in <hi>London</hi> the Seamen can buy all things at beſt hand, can ſend home their mony to their Families, to any part of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> And if they but ſpend their mony here, or ſend it home to their Families, and injoy a months Liberty, and freſh Air, and freſh Victuals, the Sea will be the next thing they will
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55757:20"/>be for; And Seamen will live and increaſe, as in other Ages of the World they uſed to do in times of War, altho Thouſands were kill'd: And of the moſt fighting War the Seamen ever ſaw in <hi>England</hi> this 100 Years, it can only be ſaid, the Sword or Guns kill'd Thouſands. But this War, without fighting, hath been the Death of <hi>ſeveral Ten Thouſands.</hi> And indeed this makes me think of their Complaints to me, ſome years paſt, that they could not Fight it out, as in former Ages: And indeed, in my mind, the Fighting like Men, and being Kill'd an Hundred in a Ship, is nothing; ſuch a loſs to themſelves, their Families, the King, and the Nation, as being kept on Board of Ship, until three or four Hundred in a Ship Die before the Voyage is done, and ſometimes a quarter of their Men Sick together; and how melancholly that muſt be, and at laſt be ſerv'd as the <hi>Mary</hi>'s Men that brought home about forty of thoſe Men they carried out, and Buried about ſix or ſeven Hundred Men, and theſe forty men not ſuffered to have a Penny of Money one Shore to Refreſh themſelves, and tell their Friends that ſome eſcaped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. I am afraid that ſome hard Hearted wretches makes as if our Seamen's Miſeries were a Comedy, but God knows whether the next Age will not call it a Tragedy, ſeeing ſuch dreadful Numbers of Lives have been loſt; but however it be, His Majeſty and the Parliament may now inquire of the Actors; how it is, and why it was ſo contriv'd, and the Charge of the whole ſeem ſo great, and ſhew no better; but my Wits run a Wool-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering: inſtead of Writing a few Heads I make ſo great Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, they will require an Hour's time to undreſs by the Fire-ſide at Night before Bed-time, and the Diſcourſe may ſeem te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: But if ſo, how tedious muſt that miſery be, when it may be a few Lives Repreſent forty Thouſand Miſeries; and I would have put in a pretty deal of Diſcourſe of Knavery alſo, as how, it may be, the King and Country may be Cheated ſhamefully: But if it be to be heard only at the <hi>Navy-Office</hi> or <hi>Admiralty-Office,</hi> as one great Cheat was, that I went about laſt Year, and Forger of Powers. And another that I went to the Commiſſioners that Stated the Publick Accounts this year, about; but they having not leiſure, I ſuppoſe the partie's peace was made up another way. But I would have had the method of Cheating to be found out above, and prevented by Law for time
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55757:20"/>to come, for the advantage of the King and the Country; for I ſuppoſe there hath been ſo many Informations of the King's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cheated, and the Seamen cheated, that have been brought before the Admiralty and Navy-board, that they know the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Knavery ten times more than I; and it may be as <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Coals to Newcaſtle,</hi> to tell them. But I wonder they have not made an out-cry to the Parliament againſt all the cheating and Knavery they have been inform'd of; for if their Skill be only in the Running and Ruining of Seamen out of their Pay when they are ſick or dead, I am ſorry; and eſpecially ſeeing I cannot find it weareth well, we have loſt ſo much this Year, our Accounts will not come even, beſides the loſs of the <hi>Hope,</hi> the <hi>Brave Hope:</hi> O that <hi>England</hi> ſhould loſe their <hi>Hope</hi> at Sea to the <hi>French</hi> this Year. And now I think of the <hi>Hope,</hi> there was five Ships of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as I underſtand, and 2 went away, and 2 run away; and there was 5 Ships of the <hi>French,</hi> and they, like cunning Knaves, kept together, and ſo got away the <hi>Hope,</hi> tho ſhe fought well. And now our brave <hi>Soveraign</hi> is burned, which is to be lamented, and for that ſhe was ſo brave a Ship, and named the <hi>Soveraign;</hi> And as for the Vulgar Name, ſome call'd her <hi>the Sufferance;</hi> As to that Name, <hi>the Sufferance,</hi> if all the Seamen's Calamities be redreſſed, I ſuppoſe they will never ſee ſuch a <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance</hi> again in haſte. But I wiſh we may ſee a brave <hi>New Hope,</hi> and as good a Ship as the other, for our Gracious King to go on board of, and name her, <hi>The New Soveraign.</hi> And ſo much to that. But,</p>
            <p>43. It might be conſidered of, that ſeeing we have loſt near 100 Ships of War theſe laſt 7 Years, to a prodigious charge to the Nation; And many people admire what is done with all the Mony raiſed, never conſidering, that ſince we ſaved our Ships from being loſt by fighting at firſt, we have loſt and fool'd away near as many ſince as will coſt Two Millions of Mony to build more, beſides the Millions of Mony extraordinary to keep an heap of Ships always in pay, tho a great many of them ſeldom ſend word home what good they do abroad. And I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thought it is poſſible to act like boys in the ſtreet, that meet before <hi>Proceſſioning-Days,</hi> great heaps and numbers, as if they would drive the Town before them; and, poor Wretches, it may be, not one in 6 hath the heart to ſtrike a ſtroke, only
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55757:21"/>run about and dirt their clothes, and put their parents to charge. But this by the way.</p>
            <p>As to our Ships loſt; for time to come, it may be uſeful for the Commiſſioners that ſtate the publick. Accounts, to have the caſe of our Ships loſt, brought before them, that if any body be in fault, they may not be all excuſed. And indeed, ſo long as the Seamen are ſent away in other Ships, and the Commanders are their own Accuſers, and their Friends the Judges, they will do well enough. I have ſometimes thought how miſchievous a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>No Body</hi> is grown ſince I was a Child; Then he uſed to be accuſed for ſtealing Apples, and eating up odd things, or drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Wine or Strong Drink in a houſe; but now, if there be Ships murdered, or fool'd away, or betray'd to the Enemies, or Fleets miſcarry, as bad as our <hi>Smirna</hi> Fleet, <hi>No Body</hi> is moſt times called to Account, and puniſhed for the ſame: And when as the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> are ruined and deſtroyed, and dead, or frighted out of the Service of our Gracious King <hi>William,</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of them, and then ſtill <hi>No Body</hi> muſt be blamed and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the ſame. And indeed, had not our moſt Gracious King <hi>William</hi> ſpoken for them, and the Loyal Parliament eſpouſed their Cauſe, to relieve them, no body would perhaps have regarded their Ruin and Deſtruction ſo long until they and their Families might have been ſome of the moſt miſerable ruined Creatures on the Face of the Earth, and no body would have gotten by their Ruin in this Nation; And yet it may be no body would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that they had been ſome of them like the poor men that travelled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Jerico,</hi> and fell among Thieves, who did not only rob them, and wound them, but did actually leave them half dead; And yet I ſuppoſe no body will be called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at laſt for all this Ruin and deſtruction of them and their Families, altho it may be the next Age will cry out ſhame of it, and ſay, the blame muſt lie ſomewhere: And it may be they will inquire then, who were thoſe at the Admiralty, or Navy-board, or in any other places, that directed and managed our Sea-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in thoſe days wherein the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> were more ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined than ever the World ſaw, and more Men of War and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Ships loſt than ever the Sea groaned under, in ſo few Years of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Concerns; and if they underſtand the true Hiſtory of this Age, they muſt know that our Gracious King <hi>William</hi> is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55757:21"/>the Juſteſt and Mercifulleſt King in the World; but is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the <hi>management of the whole Confederacy againſt that common plague of the Chriſtian World,</hi> the <hi>French King;</hi> And is forced to be be <hi>abroad,</hi> beyond Sea every Summer, to manage the Army; And that it will be known that he left the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Sea-Affairs unto <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and that to ſuch as are qualified by Law; and if there be any that wanteth any Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of Grace, or Reaſon, or Common Senſe, or Common Honeſty or Loyalty to him, it ſhould be beſt known to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for I do not meddle with Names of Men; but the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of the Seamen ſtick in my ſtomach, and I cannot digeſt it; for I am ſick of it; and had I been a Merchant, it may be I ſhould have been ſick of our Ships and Merchandize alſo. But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, it may be obſerved, That whatever miſeries or ruines come in the <hi>management of things,</hi> there is this to be conſidered of; The <hi>Managers</hi> of it muſt be men truly qualified; and that is ſomething. But I wiſh, for time to come, there may be men qualified with Grace, and Wiſdom, and Loyalty to the preſent Government, and that may have an intire Love to his Majeſty, and the good old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt, that we may not be, any of the inhabitants of theſe Nations, forced to roar like Bears, or to mourn ſore, like Doves. But <hi>I</hi> had forgot going on concerning particular incouragement for Seamen; as that they,</p>
            <p>44. Might never have ſowr Beveridge Wine forced on them in the <hi>Straits,</hi> that One Hogſhead will mix with 12 Hogſheads of Water; as is ſometimes done in the <hi>Streights,</hi> for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Purſers, tho to the hazard of Seamens Health or Lives.</p>
            <p>45. And that all Seamen might be incouraged to look out for their Enemies Ships, and that they that did ſpy them firſt, might be rewarded; And they that entred the Ships on board that are taken, might have incouragement, and not to be forced to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver every little thing they get to their Lieutenants, or Officers; And alſo it were well if there were given an Account at the Prize-Office, of the Value of Mony that hath been paid to Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men this. War, to ſee if they have had any thing to ſpeak of, or whether the Officers got all to themſelves.</p>
            <p>46. And that no Officer, on preſſing, do take any Bribes in preſſing, to exenſe the Able Seamen, and in the mean time take
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55757:22"/>Boys, and infirm perſons, or Landmen for the Service of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; And that all Preſs-Katche's Accounts be examined for time to come, to ſee if they do not put the King to 30 or 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> charge to preſs 2 or 3 men; And that no Katches bring Coals for the Officers, from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> inſtead of Seamen for the King.</p>
            <p>47. That if Ships are in Harbour, the Purſer to give the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their Allowance, as much as poſſible, in freſh proviſion, it being all on charge to his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and the way for Seamen to recover of the Scurvy, or other Sea-Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>48. That when the Seamen have been fed in the Winter, and clothed in <hi>London,</hi> and they that have Families been ſupported a Year or 2 on Credit, they may not be extorted on at <hi>Chatham,</hi> or <hi>Deal,</hi> or <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> to run in debt 18 or 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> a piece, as many have been in a fortnight, or 3 weeks time, to the Ruin of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; but that none ſhould truſt them above Half a Crown in a week, except for Clothes, or where they lodge. And that in caſe at any of thoſe Sea-Port Towns they do truſt them above that ſum, except in ſickneſs; or if they lodge there 10 <abbr>s</abbr> the week, to prevent many thouſands of Seamen running out of the Land; and that many muſt do, or hide when the War is over; For where there is a Seaman owes 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> at one houſe, and 20 at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and 10 at another, they muſt run away, and do uſually do ſo; And I have known in former time, above half thoſe who did madly truſt them, to be broken alſo: Therefore that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant expence is the Ruin of the Seamen, and thoſe who incourage them in it, and hath cauſed many Seamen to leave the Land, and go a Buckaneering in the <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> That is, to turn Pyrates, or Sea-Robbers. And now in time of War, the Pariſhes near <hi>London,</hi> are forced to relieve many Families of thoſe who ſo baſely ſpend their mony in the Sea-Port Towns; And his Majeſty's Service is often <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eglected thereby. Whereas thoſe who are good Husbands, ſave mony, and ſend it up to their Friends or Families: And theſe honeſt Seamen are ſuch as will he able to ſhow their Faces any where, if they live until time of Peace. And now I come to ſpeak of peace, I deſire the Lord in mercy to ſend a good one, if we wait a Year longer or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it comes; and our Seamen will need help in Merchant-Ships. And indeed ſome of our Merchant-Ships, the Maſters are ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſsly ſcandalouſly Villains, in going the way to cheat and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55757:22"/>the Seamen: And theſe may be reputed among the curſed Ticket-buyers, and barbarous Villains that ruin the Seamen in Men of War; For many of the Maſters in Merchant Ships ſtop what they pleaſe out of their pay, or do make them go to Law for their Wages, and keep them out oftentimes alſo 2 or 3 months, tho the poor Seamen are preſt away; And one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular lately did ſell his Seaman's Venture, and kept his pay, and the Seaman preſt away; and the Maſter did promiſe me his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from day to day, until he cunningly, in the Night, carried his Ship to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and got her cleer'd. But I heard of it in the morning, and ſent away an Officer to the Ship, and got him ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted to make him honeſt; and got the mony from the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Villain. But if Merchant Seamen were incouraged as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</p>
            <p>49. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there might be a Law made, That all Seamen might have as good and large allowance of all Proviſions and Beer, as in his Majeſtie's Ships; and in caſe of falling ſhort, on any occaſion, to be paid ſhort allowance mony alſo.</p>
            <p>50. That none might pay any dammage, except for their own Neglect or Fault. And this would be the way for Maſters and Owners to take care to ſend better Ships to Sea, and not oppreſs the Seamen for their Rotten Leaky Ships Fault.</p>
            <p>51. No Seamen to have undue Correction, nor indeed no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Correction, without the Approbation of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and 2 of the Officers, that ſo men might not be barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly killed in the Ships, as ſome have been, and others dreadfully abuſed.</p>
            <p>52. That the Maſters who ſtop 2 or 3 months pay a piece from the Seamen, when they pay them, unjuſtly, may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as Villains, that do go the way to diſcourage, and bring a Curſe on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navigation, if it lay in their power. Whereas thoſe honeſt Maſters, that Victual well, and pay well, are ſuch as go the way to incourage our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navigation, and to procure a bleſſing on the ſame; and theſe Maſters I love; but I hate all ſorts of Villany and Knavery wherever I meet with it in any: And do therefore expect to hear of ſome Knaves find Fault with this, as ſome Thieves and Cheats did when they heard I did diſcover to the Parliament how the King and Nation was cheated. But I wonder they ſhould be ſuch Fools to complain,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55757:23"/>ſeeing I named no body; And if they had laughed at it, no body had need to have known they had been guilty themſelves: And ſo I wiſh them to be wiſer next time; And tho there are Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Cheats and Villains to Cheat the King and Country, I know their methods, and am aſhamed that ſo brave and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a King, and ſo famous and fine a Country, and ſuch Stout, Loyal, brave Seamen, the beſt in the Univerſal World, ſhould be all cheated and abuſed, and that many times by thoſe who drink it away, or whore it away, or game it away. Again, and if one Devil helps them to get it, there is ſo many Devils to help to ſpend it, that ſome of them will not be worth one Groat a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, in a Years time after the War is over, and nothing ſtirring but Honeſty and Induſtry.</p>
            <p>But 53. There ought to be ſome care taken that Maſters of Ships might not abuſe, and cheat, and beat, and ſtarve their Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men beyond Sea; for that hath cauſed multitudes of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to run away in the <hi>Straits,</hi> and other Voyages, to the great diſcouragement of our brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seamen, who will do any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if incouraged; but will be mad, and run away to ſerve any Nation, yea even the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, if they are Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>54. It is pity there is not more liberal incouragement for Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to carry Ventures, and to be extraordinary well provided with proviſions in their Voyages to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> ſince many Ships have in that Voyage, of thoſe they carried out, buried 4 men to One of thoſe which they did bring home: And that is bad, to loſe all to a fifth part. And many men have in that Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age been ſuppoſed to die for want. And the Company ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by it in the danger of their Goods, if Ships miſcarry. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thoſe Brave Worthy Commanders, who Victual extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, and take great care of their men, do come home well, and their men love them, and I love them alſo for their Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and love to the Seamen. But it is a ſhame that any Ship's Commanders ſhould be ſo unnatural as to want water almoſt ſo ſoon as they come out of the Harbour: And if there were a Law made, That all Seamen in Merchant Ships ſhould be paid the full for their ſhort Allowance and Water-mony, as the King doth; And that would be the Way to incourage the Seamen to keep their Ships, and not run away to ſerve other Nations for want
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55757:23"/>of better uſage. And the Commanders of all Ships, for time to come, ought at leaſt to be made to provide Water for their Ship's Company, and not neglect it, or fraught their Ships ſo full that they have no room for Water, that ſo the poor Seamen may not be whipt at the Geers for drinking the Water that is allow'd for the Hogs. This ſeems to be worſe than the poor prodigal Son was ſerved: And indeed I have obſerved, That the <hi>Interlopers</hi> Ships to <hi>India,</hi> that their men had liberty to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Ventures, have gone well, and their men come home as fat as Pigs almoſt; as if they had not only had enough of Water, but had eaten half the Hogs alſo. And indeed it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</p>
            <p>55. Great pity that ſo many poor miſerable people were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to come and wait, and wait and come 20 times for their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after it is due, for 4 months pay, at the <hi>Eaſt India-Houſe.</hi> The loſs of time to many, and their labour, and waiting ſometimes 3 or 4 hours in a day, is worth to ſome, I fear, if they reckon their Time, above half the mony. But this Age ſeems to play with miſery. I meet with ſo many Objects of this Age's being hardned againſt the Groans of the poor, in ſome places, and Cries of the Poor, that truly I muſt needs fear that the moſt merciful God will ariſe to plead the Cauſe of the Poor, the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the Fatherleſs and the Widow, ſeeing many men ſeem to loſe moral pity. And indeed I am afraid it is gone to look after moral honeſty, many mens very Conſciences ſeeming to be even as it is ſaid of ſome Fire-Locks, Caſe-hardened: And as it is ſaid, <hi>That a good man is merciful to his beaſt;</hi> ſo I will ſay, that even the tender mercies of many wicked men in this Age, are cruel. But certainly God did not ſend men into this World to be like Devils, to plague and afflict mankind. And therefore it were well and convenient;</p>
            <p>56. That no Seamen in any Merchant Ship whatever, to be forced to wait above four Weeks after the Ship is in Harbour, for their Money, it being a very great oppreſſion on the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, after a long and tedious Voyage, to have no Mony to buy any thing for themſelves or Families in three Months time, and thereby Live on Credit, take up their Cloaths and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, at what Prices any will ſet on them, to the great Loſs of many Families.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55757:24"/>
            <p>57. But if there were a Law made for the Hearing of the Seamen's being abus'd or cheated of their Pay; and either the Maſters of the <hi>Trinity-Houſe,</hi> or ſome other men, to be as a Court of Conſcience to hear the Seamen's Cauſe, without Charge, it would ſave the poor Seamen's being forc'd to go to Law for their Wages after any Voyage, or for mony to be paid in the time of any Voyage, it might ſave a multitude of Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at Law, or loſs to poor miſerable Seamen, or their Families being often forc'd to give one half to get the other Recovered, after it is Earn'd.</p>
            <p>58. Another method for the true management of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navigation, is to labour to have both the Commanders and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Seamen, to be brought to a moral Reformation, and alſo to a Religious Worſhip, and fear of the God of Heaven and Earth, and Sea, at whoſe Command are both Winds and Seas, and indeed if God be not ſought unto, but inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, dayly Blaſphemed all other ways and means will be too ſhort to Expect a real Bleſſing, and comfortable Incouragement, as we might wiſh; but that the Seamen will be ſo much oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Ships Ruined and Spoiled, more and more, until there be ſome outward Reformation at leaſt, if not a true and ſound Reformation of Life and Manners. And if the general inſtructions printed and given to the Captains and Lieutenants of Ships by the Admiralty, were minded aright, it would mend many things, and therefore deſerves to be inquired into, in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the method of the Well-Government of our Ships and men; And the firſt Paragraph of it is, <hi>That God be duly worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and that twice a day, and all Profaneneſs, Drunkenneſs, Swearing and Curſing be diſcountenanced and puniſhed; and the Commanders that allow it, turned out.</hi> And we ſhould meet the Lord by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance both by Sea and Land; and cry to the Lord, that he would meet us with his mercy, that we may, by Righteouſneſs, be an exalted Nation, and not for our ſins be a ruined people: And therefore,</p>
            <p>59. It were well if every Ship in <hi>England</hi> that carrieth but ten men were bound to carry that excellent Book of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Doctrine, the Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> to read 2 <hi>Homilies</hi> every <hi>Sunday.</hi> And it hath the 39 Articles bound up with it, that all Seafaring men might ſee the excellent Doctrine of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55757:24"/>Old Church of <hi>England</hi> to be for ſound Piety and Holineſs: And that it may be ſaid of the Prophaneneſs of this Age, That it is ſuch a thing as the Fundamental Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> abhors: And as it was ſaid of Old, of ſome that knew not <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſo it may be ſaid of the great Wickedneſs of this Age, That it is from ſuch as know not God, neither do they truly know, and believe, and practice that true fundamental Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> And it were well if the Reverend Biſhops would conſult the great need there is of ſuch Laws as may in ſome meaſure at leaſt bring men to as near a Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the ſubſtantial, Fundamental Holineſs, Sobriety, Charity, Juſtice, and all Chriſtian, Fundamental Duties of Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs that are contained in ſo holy a Doctrine.</p>
            <p>60. And that every Ship that doth carry 120 men, or more, do carry an able, ſober Miniſter, to inſtruct the Seamen in their Duty towards God, and to reprove the Vices of any one in the Ship; And by their Doctrine and Converſation, to ſhew to them that the fundamental Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is for the Real Service of God and Holineſs, and againſt all ſin; And that they that profeſs the Doctrine, and live in Wickedneſs, are falſe pretenders to ſo holy Doctrine.</p>
            <p>61. And therefore that Excellent Act againſt Curſing and Swearing, if well executed, will be a good beginning, and a good help towards a moral Reformation. So if the great Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this Age could be ſuppreſſed, it would be a good help to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men's coming to conſider of a future ſtate, and to think, that whatever they are themſelves at preſent, yet mankind was created to live to the Glory of God, and to honour him; and not to live like beaſts, and worſe than beaſts. And the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent the fundamental Doctrine of Chriſtianity is in any Church or Nation, the greater the condemnation of thoſe muſt be that do ſin againſt the Light of the ſame, and will not regard to walk according unto it.</p>
            <p>And now having ſaid this, I will return again to another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement I think there is great need of, altho the Seamen in all <hi>Merchant</hi> Ships, that go well and come well, in the <hi>Merchant's</hi> ſervice, pay ſomething towards the ſame; And that is,</p>
            <p>62. That all Fleets of Merchant Ships ſhould, as much as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, keep company, and ſtand by one the other, except much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-powered;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55757:25"/>And for want of this there was 6 or 7 Ships ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of 12 in One Fleet, by 2 <hi>Privateers.</hi> Therefore thoſe Ships that would not fight, the <hi>Commanders</hi> ought to be made publick Examples.</p>
            <p>63. And thoſe that fight ſtoutly, as brave <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> to be incouraged and preferred.</p>
            <p>64. And that thoſe Seamen that loſe their Lives or Limbs in <hi>Merchant</hi> ſhips, ſhould be incouraged, and have Bounty-mony, as in his Majeſties ſervice they that are Wounded or Kill'd there have.</p>
            <p>But now I would not be miſtaken, to think that his Majeſty ſhould pay it; altho if a <hi>Merchant</hi> Ship be loſt, it may fall out that his Majeſty may loſe 4000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> Cuſtom: And were it ſo they did fight and ſave the Ship and Goods, if there were 20 kill'd, and 10 wounded, if his Majeſty paid each of them, or their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> it were 200 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> and his Majeſty would ſave 3600 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> by the ſaving the Ship at laſt, and the Merchants, it may be, 30000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> by the bargain alſo: And therefore it would be of great uſe to the King and to the Merchants, and to the Nation in general, to ſave our Ships as much as poſſible, and ruin our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies as much as poſſible, and encourage our Seamen and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to fight, to ſave the Ships as much as poſſible. But I have often wondred that any Merchants ſhould be ſo barbarous, or Maſters ſo uncharitable, as not to give the Seamens Families one penny of Eucouragement, who laid down their Lives, and ſaved their Ships. And ſometimes I have heard of ſome that have been forc'd to go to Law for their Wages after the Ship was ſaved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as I remember, a Cuſtomer of mine was forced to pay the Chirurgeon 3 or 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> to cure him of his Wounds. Now I did look on this <hi>as barbarous:</hi> And I do ſay, in this reſpect, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is much better than the <hi>Merchant-men;</hi> And would be in many others alſo, if it were not for the Fault of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and Officers of divers ſorts. But this by the way; for I think we ſhould be the moſt <hi>happy people under the Face of Heaven,</hi> if it were not for the Sins, and Follies, and Bribery, and Knave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Villany of the Age we live in; Whereby men are Ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and plagued and Afflicted more than ever, in ſeveral Kinds, both in <hi>Men of War and Merchant</hi> Ships, and the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try loſe by the ſame at laſt, many Seamen ſerving, as is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55757:25"/>other Nations, by being ſo much diſcouraged in their own: But I leave that, and would to God that all would indeed leave it in good earneſt, and ſet themſelves to ſtudy to ſerve God and his Majeſty, and the common good of all theſe Nations; and in order to it, I think this is one, to incourage all Seamen, as much as poſſible, to preſerve our Shipping; and one way was, that, as I ſaid, <hi>Whoever loſt their Limbs or Lives in defending a Merchant Ship, ſhould have Penſions, or Bounty-mony:</hi> And I ſuppoſe, that if there were a Law made, That every one ſhould be ſo rewarded, every Seaman would be more willing to venture their Lives to ſave their Ships: and the very Seamen in Merchant Ships, that went well and came well, would pay 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d</hi>
               </abbr> out of every pound towards a Cheſt to be kept for that purpoſe at <hi>Greenwich</hi> Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, as there is a Cheſt for the Cripples at <hi>Chatham:</hi> And there might be a Commiſſioner, or 2 or 3, appointed to manage it in time of War and Peace: And in time of War, they that are in Merchant Ships could afford to pay that cheerfully, becauſe their Wages is near double; and in time of Peace it might be but 6<abbr>d</abbr> in the pound towards the Penſions; and a Clerk or 2 appointed at the ſaid Hoſpital, to keep all accounts of every mans months pay in <hi>England,</hi> and to receive the mony, and to pay it out again to the Widow or Aged Parents of all that are kill'd in the defence of Merchant Ships, 20<abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> and to all that loſe a Limb, or the total uſe of a Limb, in the defence of a Merchant Ship, 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> the year during their Lives; for their Relief; and this to be paid them conſtantly: And not to have any Ticket-buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſuffered to extort half of it from them: And if the ſaid ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the pound paid by others, did amount to more, as it might, if gathered faithfully all over the Nation, then the reſt to go to the Widows of poor Seamen, or to aged Seamen that were paſt their labour. And it is as great pity, but all induſtrious Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould be incouraged in <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing I do not remember that ever in all my Life I heard of one Ship, either Merchant Man, or Man of War loſt, becauſe the Seamen would not fight; but ſo many becauſe the Commanders would not fight, that I have been ofter grieved and aſhamed to hear of it. And if there were a Law made to incourage the Seamen, I wiſh there were alſo another, That if the Commander<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would not fight, they ſhould loſe, as aforeſaid, 2 of their ſingers, and be ſold for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55757:26"/>ſaves all their days; and if they did ever return, to be hanged, that ſo there may not be ſo many to diſgrace this brave Iſland with Cowardiſe, which hath been, and in ſome meaſure is, at this day the Terror of their Enemies, the <hi>French</hi> Fleet; which were pretended to be ſuch Monſters before; having run to their Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours with ſhame and diſgrace, ſince they ſee we have an Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral who with leſs than half our Ships did beat them before; and for that we have cauſe to bleſs God, and live to his Praiſe.</p>
            <p>And now to ſay ſomething to ſave his Majeſty's mony, and the poor Seamens alſo, for time to come, I do ſuppoſe it will be needful for time to come, to make it Felony to commit theſe Tranſgreſſions, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To enter 40 mens Names in a Ship's book, that never were in the Ship, nor in the World, and that is bigger; This to be Felony. And this is a Trick of the Devil's Maſterpiece.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no Purſer, or Captain's Clerk, or any other, do give a Liſt of 40 or 50 men at a time, that are dead, or run away; that ſo, tho the King hath been cheated of their Victuals, he may not be cheated of their Pay; and tho the Purſer might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford their Pay cheap, yet I wondred when I heard One Purſer gave as many Names as there was 3 or 400 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> worth received for in a Ship, and the fooliſh Knave had but 8 or 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> for all. Now this Purſer, and they that did find Powers, ought to be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed on of this Nation, that the Climate may not be infected with their Villany.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That no man in the Office be ſuffered to change the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Name of a Seaman in any Ships books, to cheat the man's Friends of his mony, if occaſion be: This Exploit looks like the Art of Jugling, if it ſhould be practiſed; therefore ſhould, if diſcovered, be puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That none be ſuffered to keep men open upon the book a whole Voyage after they are run away, ſince this Trick, and thoſe before-mentioned, and ſome Captains, as I here diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have many hundred pounds worth of Seamens Tickets, and ſome other Tricks I know may be plaid, if not prevented, may coſt his Majeſty it may be 80000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> the Year, and cheat the Seamen Twenty Thouſand Pounds to make it up an Hundred Thouſand Pounds the Year; and it being hard Times, as I find it is, a penny ſav'd will be as good as a peuny got; And if others
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55757:26"/>do ſtudy to raiſe ſo much, it is their Ingenuity; and if I do ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy how to ſave his Majeſty and the Nation 100000<abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> the year, it may be a ſervice for the Nation, altho it may be no great inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in me for my ſelf, becauſe I am not like to get any profit to my ſelf by it in this world: but I bleſs God who enableth me in ſome meaſure to be willing to ſerve his Majeſty and theſe Nations; as cheerfully, and heartily, and faithfully, for Love, as any man alive can do for Mony; And if the Repreſenting theſe laſt, or any other Knavery, ſhould cauſe any to be offended at me, I ſhould wonder at their folly and madneſs to betray them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſince I love and reſpect every honeſt loyal Commander and Officer in his Majeſty's ſervice, and every honeſt good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in Merchant-men; and they that are ſuch will no doubt love me, and delight in me, as one that is willing that every man of their Profeſſions and Offices ſhould be an honour to the ſame, and to get praiſe to the whole Fraternity of them. But I expect that thoſe who are ſore, and ſcabbed, and gall'd, will, as we uſe to ſay, be ready, when their ſore is touch'd, to winch and kick, altho I name no perſon; I wiſh their perſon well, and their Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Villany puniſhed, and they made better. And I only repreſent the Knavery, and if they will be ſo fooliſh when they hear it, by their Anger to let others know they are the men, that is their fault; and <hi>a guilty conſcience needs no accuſer.</hi> And ſo I leave them to their ſerious conſiderations, to think if they have ſouls, how they that are Cheats and Villains here, muſt anſwer it hereafter.</p>
            <p>And I wiſh all mankind well, and know no man alive but I would do a kindneſs to, if it lay in my way; and know not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man alive but would do the ſame by me. And now being come to a concluſion of this, I give up this and my ſoul, ſpirit, body, and all my Family, and all my affairs, all into the hands of the Eternal Love and Mercy of our moſt gracious God and loving Father in Jeſus Chriſt our only Saviour, for all time, and all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:55757:27"/>
            <head>The Art of Ticket-buying, or the way to help to Ruin the Seamen and their Families in their Service and Pay. In a Diſcourſe between <hi>Honesty, Poverty, Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Villany,</hi> as follows.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hsneſty.</speaker>
               <p>THIS Trade of Ticket-buying doth ſeem to have its Riſe between Miſery and Cruelty, or between cheating the King and Country, and Ruining the Seamen in their Pay; and as times grow worſe, either in manners or miſery, this Trade grows and increaſes as Miſleto doth on a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying Apple-Tree; as the Tree decays the Miſle increaſeth: at firſt <hi>Cruelty</hi> uſed to buy at 5 <abbr>s</abbr> profit in the pound, from the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; but that was near 30 years paſt, and they were cried out upon as extortioning Villains then, that have paſſed as modeſt men ſince: but ſince the times are grown more impudent in cheating the King, and ruining the Seamen, there be many have bought the Seamens pay at half loſs; and not only content with that, but like inhumane Beaſts, that were worſe than all other ſort of Beaſts, except Swine, in devouring their own Kind, there have been ſome that have bought at near Two Thirds Loſs, and others, worſt of all, have many of them ſwallowed up the poor Seamens Pay altogether, for nothing, except the charge of an Oath, and falſe Power, if dead, or a falſe Power, if out of the way, as hath of late been often proved: And this Villany and Extortion, and cheating the Loyal Seamen out of their Pay, hath been an unknown loſs to the King, and unknown Ruin to the Seamens Families, and unknown Loſs to thoſe who did friendly and honeſtly truſt the Seamen, who by reaſon of their loſing 7 or 8 <abbr>l</abbr> at a time, out of a Ticket bought by <hi>Cruelty,</hi> or being
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55757:27"/>ſhameleſly deprived of it all by <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llany,</hi> have not been able to pay their Debts, neither buy bread for themſelves and Families as they ought to do. And indeed what ſay you <hi>Poverty,</hi> is it not ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed we have found it ſo, for while we have been ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled from Ship to Ship, until our Friends knew not where to find us, it hath been an Opportunity for <hi>Villany</hi> to get Powers to cheat us of all our Pay: or if we fell ſick and died, for others to Q or R us; living, out of our Pay, if dead, to deprive our Wives and poor ruined Children. But, <hi>Honeſty,</hi> it ſeems, knows not what Names to call thoſe by that Ruin the Living, and fright many of them away; and Run the Dead, and let their Families cry for Juſtice or Vengeance; and he knows not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the next Age will call them barbarous Villains, or hard hearted Wretches, or Fools, or Knaves, or Jacobites, and Friends to <hi>French,</hi> or a mixture of all together, and Ruiners of their Country into the bargain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
               <p>Do not ſay what I think; for if ſo, you will ſay the laſt Age the Devil and the Jeſuits debauched many people out of Religion and Morality, and now they would, if they could, cheat us out of our common Senſes, and out of all our mony in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bargain, this next year or two; and there is too much cauſe of fear of this. But you muſt ſay little of it for the fear of puzling. But as to the Loſs of ſenſes, you may tell our Enemies of it; for it may be they know not how they have loſt them, neither where to find them again, they are ſo dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled away; or waſht away. And as to the Loſs of our Mony, you may let your Friends know of it; for your Enemies know it is worth more, our mill'd mony, to melt down, or carry to <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Sweedland,</hi> and ſome other parts, b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ten in the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſome places, and near Twenty in other places; and they begin to laugh and ſay, Where is your mony? And that is too ſad to make a Jeſt of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Villany.</speaker>
               <p>What a noiſe here is of mony: If I can buy Tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets at Ten ſhillings in the pound, I will buy; have you any?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>I have a ſmall Ticket to ſell; I am in great diſtreſs. I was in ſuch a Ship, and fell ſick, and was Run out of my mony: but I crawled into the King's ſervice again, and now I have a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55757:28"/>Ticket of 6 or 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> and we have not a penny to buy a bit of Bread for my Family, neither a Rag of Cloaths for my ſelf, and yet I have been in the ſervice all this War; what will you give me for my Ticket, <hi>Cruelty?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay you were Run out of your Pay before, for being ſick; and who knows, tho you are diſcharged fair now, and have a Ticket, but you may go into another Ship, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue there until you fall ſick, and be Run out of your Pay there, and for this alſo? However I will give you 40 <abbr>s</abbr> for your Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, <hi>Poverty,</hi> if you pleaſe: What ſay you, <hi>Poverty,</hi> will you take it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poverty's Wife.</speaker>
               <p>That is very hard, and our Caſe is miſerable, however, mony we muſt have; my poor Husband has not a penny to buy him a Shirt, or a pair of Shooes or Stockings to ſhift him, and I do not ſee what we can do; pray give me 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> for it, and that is dreadful Loſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>No, I will give you 50 <abbr>s</abbr> I do not know whether my brother <hi>Cruelty,</hi> or my ſiſter <hi>Villany</hi> would give ſo much; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do what pou will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>Wife, take the mony: who ſhall make the Writings? Pray what Writings muſt you have?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt have a Bill of Sale, will coſt you 18 <abbr>
                     <hi>d</hi>
                  </abbr> and a Letter of Attorney, will coſt you 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> My brother <hi>Cruelty</hi> does uſe to have a Bond too, which would coſt 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> or 18<abbr>
                     <hi>d</hi>
                  </abbr> more; and my ſiſter <hi>Cruelty</hi> does uſe to have a ſmall piece of meat, and ſome good drink alſo when ſhe payeth the mony: but I would have you ſee I am kind to you: and if any of <hi>your Ship's Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> hath any more Tickets, I will buy them; for I have ſome mony lies by me that I received at the Office lately; and if they will ſell them, I will help them to mony for them, if they be good; ſend them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>I have ſome mony due in ſuch a Ship; it ſtands open on the book, and they are not to let me ſee the book without petitioning the Navy-board, and I have not a penny of mony in all the World to get the Petition written, and I know not what to do: I ſpend my time in the waiting for the payment of the Ship; will you buy it, <hi>Cruelty,</hi> what ſay you?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:55757:28"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>If I get the books ſearched, you muſt pay the charge, and if we agree, and muſt give me Bond, if I <hi>buy it,</hi> to make it good to me, if it be made <hi>Run</hi> in the Office, as many have been.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>How ſhould it be made <hi>Run</hi> in the Office, when I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged fair, and have been in ſo many Ships ſince, and not had a penny of mony for any of them, and my Family not had a penny of the King's Pay to buy them one bit of bread, neither my ſelf a penny to buy a Rag of Cloaths to cover my Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this 2 or 3 Years: And I have been in 2 or 3 Ships more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides: Pray what will the books coſt ſearching privately? Pray be as kind as you can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>I will not Undertake to get them ſearched under half a Crown.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>Pray get it done, and I will abate it out of the mony, if we agree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>I have got the books ſearched, and I find there is 6<abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> 10<abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> due to <hi>you,</hi> if it be paid at laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>I did reckon I had been 8 months in the Ship, and my mony had come to 9 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> But I muſt take <hi>your word:</hi> What will <hi>you give me for the mony?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>I will give you 30 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> for it; and I know not if it will be ever paid: There is an Order, <hi>That if a man fall ſick in the laſt Ship, and be run of his Pay in that, they do make him run out of his Pay in other Ships:</hi> Therefore do what you pleaſe with it, and I have been at charge to get the books ſearched, and do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>you ſhall pay me that.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>I have not one Groat, if it were to ſave my ſelf and Family from Ruin and ſtarving: Therefore if <hi>you do not buy it,</hi> I cannot pay you: take it for 40 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> anp <hi>pay</hi> the charges beſides.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>No, I will allow <hi>you</hi> 34 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> and abate <hi>you</hi> all charges for Writings, and all will be about 6<abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> more, and that is 40<abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> in all together, tho <hi>you</hi> have but 34<hi>s. you ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poverty.</speaker>
               <p>Take it: I cannot wait: and my poor Wife is forced to work hard for bread for our Children, to keep them from ſtarving, or being kept by the Pariſhes: And we owe mony to the Baker, and to the poor Chandler-woman, and that for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Bread, or Cheeſe, or now and then a quartern of Butter, to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55757:29"/>help to keep my poor Family: And I owe for the Cloaths and Bedding I had to ſit me out to Sea, or I might have periſhed for Cold, and not been able to ſerve the King, and this poor lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mony cannot pay one Groat of thoſe Debts to either: And I being turn'd from Ship to Ship, if <hi>I</hi> am forc'd to ſell the reſt ſo, none knows what <hi>I</hi> and <hi>my poor Family</hi> muſt do to live. This will not hardly <hi>buy</hi> me Shirts and Drawers, and a Waſtcoat and Coat, and Shooes, to fit me to Sea again: and I ſhall hardly be able to let my Wife add Children have 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> of this mony: And for the mony I owe <hi>Honeſty,</hi> he muſt ſtay, and that is pity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a man hath been very ready to truſt the Seamen to ſerve the King, and that as cheap as for <hi>ready mony,</hi> and hath loſt abundance by the ſame, and is forced to hold his hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be too late, and he ruin himſelf to help them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Villany.</speaker>
               <p>As to him you call <hi>Honeſty, I</hi> hate the Name of him, and intend never to have to do with him, he is ſo much a Fool<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> He had for a Year or 2 half ſpoiled this Trade of Ticket-buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for he bought up almoſt all the Tickets that came near him, at 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> in the Pound Profit to himſelf, and we could get but a few of thoſe, who did not know where to find ſuch a one of the Trade: And at laſt he bought at Three Shillings in the Pound Profit: And finding himſelf then to have now and then a Delay, he began to be weary of the Trade: and ſince, he and many of his Friends left off buying <hi>Cruelty</hi> can come in, for ſome buſineſs by Wholeſale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>The more is the pity that ſo few of his Friends will now <hi>buy any poor Seaman's Pay:</hi> And it is ſad for the poor Rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Seamen. But it ſeems he was ſerved worſe at the Office than the <hi>Heathen Romans</hi> uſed to do in point of Juſtice: for he bought One Ticket in a Ship called the <hi>Roſe,</hi> from <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of Fifty Pound, and paid Forty Five Pound for it: and it was clear of all incumbrances when he bought it: and ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Laſt Captain, and Purſer <hi>Swain,</hi> and all the ſigning Officers, clear of all Debt. But ſome of the Commiſſioners laid a ſtop on it for the Uſe of the former Captain's Mother: and w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n petitioned about it, could neither tell wherefore, nor where <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> find her, and yet continued the ſtop: made <hi>Poor Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arlick</hi> wait near Two Years, and loſe the intereſt of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55757:29"/>aboot ſix Pound, be at the charge to go and ſend into City and Country, to find out the Captain's Mother: and one of their Officers gave them under his Hand, he had enquired, and ſhe could not be found: And after waiting ſo long, and the party that earned the mony appearing, who was preferr'd to a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant's Place, and demanding his mony to be paid to <hi>Honeſty,</hi> his Attorney; and ſaid, <hi>None other ever had power from him:</hi> And yet they would not let it be paid, until a <hi>Lawyer</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and claimed ſome mony due to the Captain, but had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſhow for it; and then the ſtop was taken off lamely; that is to be paid to them that had the beſt <hi>Power,</hi> when there was never any Power they could find or hear of, ever to appear for it, beſides <hi>poor filly Honeſty:</hi> and he was Kept out of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny until the books were made up, and then had it paid by a Liſt: and then Purſer <hi>Swain,</hi> that was Purſer of the Ship, had five Pound ſtopped out of it for Tobacco, altho there was none due, and doth detain the mony ſtill, altho he hath heard of it ſo much: and <hi>poor Noneſty</hi> knows not whether he did not loſe twice as much by his mony being ſtopped ſo unjuſtly from him <hi>by the Commiſſioners,</hi> or <hi>by the</hi> 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> ſtopped for the Purſer, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which of them all will be the honeſteſt men when <hi>they</hi> come to die, or look blackeſt in the face Living or Dying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cruelty.</speaker>
               <p>You have told ſome part how <hi>Honeſty</hi> was ſerved in that Caſe, that he never would ſpeak of; but you have not told how many Tickets he hath by him, or his Friends, that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is ſaid to be paid the parties, and they know not where to find the parties; and <hi>Honeſty</hi> never told the Riddle of that Trick, That if poor Seamens Wives have their Husbands Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets detained by the Captains, they may cry their Eyes out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they get a penny of Mony without Tickets: But when Tickets are in ſome hands, then mony can be ſaid to be paid the parties, or to <hi>Jack-a-Noaks,</hi> or <hi>Joan-a-Styles;</hi> and the Tickets may ſerve for the Ages to come, to wonder why there ſhould not be a certain Rule, a certain Payment, and a certain Law in the Seamens Payment; and not lay all the blame on <hi>Cruelty,</hi> in buying; for he commonly gives ſomething for what he buyeth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55757:30"/>of the Seamen, altho but little; but <hi>Villany</hi> cheats them of all: And his brother <hi>Villany</hi> us'd to give ſomething for what he buys of the Officers, tho they all cheat the King, or the Seamen, ſhamefully.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
               <p>Now I think of it, pray <hi>Honeſty,</hi> I do hear, ſince you made ſuch a Noiſe this 2 Years, of ſome Officers cheating the King, and the Seamen of their Tickets and Pay, there is an Order, <hi>they muſt receive no man's Pay but their own;</hi> and I hear ſome of them are vexed ſadly at You: What muſt they do now with ſuch Tickets, pray, to get a penny for them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Honeſty.</speaker>
               <p>I will not ſay what they muſt do, but I will ſay, if they be not prevented; they that pleaſe to give their mind to it, and have Tickets at their command, I fear can get Powers fill'd up, and witneſſed by themſelves, or other Officers, and leave Blanks for ſuch Names to receive them, as may ſerve to be put in afterwards: And therefore it was my Advice, That if the Parliament pleaſed, they ſhould make it Felony and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation to receive a Seaman's <hi>Pay</hi> by a wrong power, for time to come: And if they had been Seamen, and cheated of their <hi>Pay,</hi> ten times as often as men have Robbed on the High-way, or had their Pockets pickt at Land, they would have ſtriv'd to make a Law againſt cheating, for time tu come, and not left it to will and pleaſure, to hinder ſmall Officers from receiving mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by a Lawful Power, although they fed them and cloathed them ſeveral Years before, to aſſiſt them whsle they ſerved the King, and in the mean time leave ſo many ways open to cheat the King and the Seamen by other Officers ſtill in private ways, inſtead of thoſe Hundreds of Pounds in a Ship received for the Captains, of Seamens <hi>Pay</hi> publickly, in former Years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poverty.</speaker>
               <p>It is a Wonder that you will meddle with ſuch Diſeaſes as are <hi>Noli me tangeries;</hi> that though they are heard of publickly now and then, as the <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> is in the <hi>Weekly Bill,</hi> yet hardly One in an Hundred knows what a dreadful Diſtemper it is, although ſome die of the ſame: And therefore, pray if you meet with any Offices that are infected
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55757:30"/>with the Ruining and Plaguing of the Seamen, as the Houſes of ſome were of Old in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the Leproſie, that they could never be cleanſed until the very Walls were ſcraped; And although the whole Prieſthood ſhould by the Law of God Judge them Unclean, pray <hi>Honeſty</hi> ſay no more of it. And when you hear <hi>I</hi> have been ſick a Year or Two, or in the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals, and Run out of my Pay, to the Ruin of my Family; and <hi>I</hi> and <hi>my Family</hi> cry and groan to Heaven for Relief or Vengeance; and others of my <hi>Poor Poverty Brethren</hi> be cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Heaven and Hell for Damnation againſt them that Ruin them, and Run away to other Nations, to ſee if there be <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> there; pray hold your Peace for time to come; Let things ſink or ſwim, you have done your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and you being ſenſible every Leaf you write, muſt be ſuch as muſt be true before God and man, as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it. And now you may admire at the mercy of God in keeping you hitherro, as in mercy you have been hitherto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Honeſty.</speaker>
               <p>That is true, and that <hi>I</hi> only truſt to the infinite Free Grace, and Free Love and Rich mercy of God to me and all mine, in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord and only Saviour, for all Time and all Eternity, deſiring the Eternal God to be our Refuge and Portion for ever: And that underneath us may be his Everlaſting Arms of Love and mercy, for all Time and all Eternity, to us and all ours. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poverty.</speaker>
               <p>You have choſen well: but do not you conſider, That there was an Age wherein it was ſaid, <hi>Hold thy peace, for we may not mention the Name of our God?</hi> But do not you think, that thoſe ſad and barbarous Villains, who do Cheat, and Ruin, and Deſtroy the Seamens Pay and Families in this Age, do neither fear God, nor Regard man, but are as Ungodly, Hard-hearted, Caſe-hardned Brutes, that ſeem as the Boy ſaid by his Learning the <hi>Primmer,</hi> ſome of them <hi>to be paſt the Graces,</hi> and to be come almoſt as far as the Devil and all his Works: And as it was ſaid of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman by his Jackanapes, <hi>An Ill Life may Expect an Ill
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55757:31"/>End.</hi> Therefore pray be wary how you Diſcourſe about thoſe ſort of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Honeſty.</speaker>
               <p>I bleſs God <hi>I</hi> have no prejudice againſt the Perſons of any men in <hi>England;</hi> and know not any man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> but <hi>I</hi> would ſhew him a civil kindneſs; and it may be there is hardly a man but would do the like by me, if occaſion were; and <hi>I</hi> find Anger is often Folly, but malice is the Devil, and a dreadful burden certainly for any man to carry: and <hi>I</hi> bleſs God who keeps me clear of that hitherto, as <hi>I</hi> deſire to be kept from flattery, and that makes me write ſuch plain honeſt homely <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> to ſerve my King and Country, without much minding who are pleaſed or diſpleaſed: and that makes me labour as heartily to endeavour the preſerving of our Lives and Liberties, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seamen, with as much earneſtneſs as ever <hi>I</hi> heard of any did to ſecure a Wall or Bank that was to keep out the Sea from drowning the Country: And therefore having ſaid it may be too much, <hi>I</hi> may paſs over a great part of <hi>the Art of Ticket-buying</hi> in ſilence, for want of Time and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo ſay little of the <hi>Buyers</hi> Skill in getting the poor Wretches in that are not in the greateſt of miſeries, making them drunk, and getting their <hi>Pay as they pleaſe:</hi> Or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buying at Five Shillings, and paying them part of their money, and then afterwards will have them at Ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings Profit, or demand their money again, and extort money for. Extortioning Intereſt, beſides Trouble, if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pay the money. Neither mind <hi>I</hi> to repreſent how there have been ſome Hundreds of Pounds worth of Tickets offered without Powers at a time in One Ship: Neither the making out of Twenty Hogs, <hi>alias,</hi> Seamens Tickets in One Ship, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed about Fifty men: Neither the very great multitudes of Tickets Captains Clerks have made out privately for Seamens Pay: Neither need <hi>I</hi> trouble my Head for time to come, much more than other men, if the King and the Nation ſhould ever be found to be cheated of a ſixth part of their money: for if <hi>I</hi> pay about Twelve Pound the Year this War: Taxes, as <hi>I</hi> have done, it is but Forty ſhillings Charge Extraordinary the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55757:31"/>Year: And <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe <hi>I</hi> have printed as many Thouſand ſheets of Paper, freely to inform the moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament, and theſe Nations this Laſt Three Years, as hath coſt me about Ten Years Purchaſe, for my ſixth part of the ſaid Twelve Pound: And <hi>I</hi> bleſs God <hi>I</hi> was never imployed by any to do it, but as the good will and pleaſure of God ſtirred me up out of a true deſign to ſerve God, and my King and Country: and <hi>I</hi> never had, to my knowledge, Ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings advantage from all others for the ſame. And <hi>I</hi> am of no Club, nor of no Faction; neither am <hi>I</hi> any mens <hi>Inſtrument</hi> or <hi>Tool:</hi> ſo that if <hi>I</hi> do any ſervice, the glory will be to God, and the benefit to theſe Nations: And if <hi>I</hi> miſtake, and ſuffer for it, <hi>I</hi> muſt ſubmit with Humility, Love and Patience. And ſo intreating the pardon of his moſt gracious <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the Two moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament, for what is amiſs: and begging of the Eternal Jehovah for his Grace and Bleſſing on his Majeſty, our moſt gracious King <hi>William,</hi> and on the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and People of theſe Nations: and on me and all my Family, I ſubſcribe my ſelf a faithful Subject to his Majeſty, and Servant to him and all good men, while <hi>I</hi> remain to be,</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. HODGES.</signed>
               <dateline>Hermitage-Bridge, <date>Feb. <hi>20th. 1695.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:55757:32"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce I writ my firſt book of the Seamens miſeries, and preſented 500 of them to the 2 moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament, who were graciouſly pleaſed to paſs by my infirmities, in repreſenting the fame; for which I am in all humble duty obliged to be thankful to them. And I have preſumed to attempt the foregoing rough Peice, being heartily willing any that can repreſent better Rules for the ſafety and encouragement of the Seamen, to ſerve his gracious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty King <hi>William,</hi> and the Nation, I ſhall rejoice. But if any ſay, ſome did by my other book, they could have repreſented it in fewer as words, and yet never had themſelves neither wit, or ſenſe, or heart for to repreſent it at all, I ſhall look on their words as idle prate, and to try their skill, if they are excellent at any thing, I will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the miſerable Caſe of our Trading People, and the poor in theſe Nations, in reſpect of our mony, which I fear the loſs of will be fatal to both: And I wiſh it may not be miſerable in reſpect of the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Taxes for his Majeſty: for I fear that as our Mill'd Money was bought up to carry away, or melted down, above 20 years, when it was worth but a Groat in the pound to make it away; then I fear it will be ten times more in danger to be all melted down or carried away, or both, now it is worth ten Groats in the pound to make it away either way. Neither do I ſee how Tradeſmen can eſcape Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for want of Trade, if there be not mony to Trade, and Exchange, and pay the poor. And the Loſs of Trade already to ſome I fear hath been, and is like to be ten times worſe than their Taxes; and unleſs there be a new Coinage, that is about 3 Ounces to 20 <abbr>s</abbr> or the Mill'd mony raiſed to 6 <abbr>s</abbr> and 8 <abbr>
                  <hi>d</hi>
               </abbr> the Crown Peice, I fear whoever lives 9 months, will ſee hardly any of it paſſing about; and for Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea's, they are at preſent a perfect Plague and Trick to mankind, and a means for men to prey upon one another; and if they fall, will be carried away; but if ſetled at but 28 <abbr>
                  <hi>s</hi>
               </abbr> the Guinea certain, would pay in Taxes, and out again; and there might be One <hi>per Cent.</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for profit of thoſe who carried Silver and Gold to Coin; and the reſt to go towards the Calling in the Fragments of our Old Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at laſt; And there would never want Silver nor Coiners; and we ſhould be in a few Years full of mony, to the Joy of the King and Country, and Landlord and Tenant: And this I would repreſent,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55757:32"/>that our Seamen at Sea, and the common people at Land, tho called the <hi>Mobilly,</hi> have been entirely in the Intereſt of our gracious King <hi>William,</hi> and this Nation. And I fear our Enemies would rejoice it they could find the Ordinary people to be Ruined at Land for want of mony; and then they would ſay, as they begin already, <hi>Where is your mony?</hi> and I fear, if poſſible, will make the worſt uſe they could of the ſame. And, if I miſtake not, our Caſe in the Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> is ſo bad already, that One may go to ten Tradeſmen before One meet with a man can change a Guinea: So that here is Work for the Wits to <hi>propoſe a help</hi> that is paſt my skill to think or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how ever the <hi>common people</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſhall keep Silver mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any more, if there be none but what is <hi>worth a great deal more to melt down, or carry away:</hi> They may kiſs it at parting, as Friends that do never expect to ſee One the Other more, I fear; and have not ſenſe to get over my fears, but reſt in them this 27th of <hi>Feb.</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>By reaſon of the Author's great diſtance from the Preſs, there is divers</hi> Errata<hi>'s, which the Courteois Reader is deſired to correct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ERRATA.</p>
            <p>PAge 4. line 6. read <hi>formerly.</hi> p. 9. l. 14. r. <hi>he would.</hi> p. 9. 1. 16. r. <hi>I might.</hi> p. 10. r. 14. <hi>January.</hi> p. 15. l. 28. r. <hi>Once a year or two.</hi> p. 21. l. 29. r. <hi>not having.</hi> p. 25. l. 6. r. <hi>Breamen.</hi> p. 26. l. 35. r. <hi>Imbezzlement. Ibid.</hi> l. 11. r. <hi>in the laſt Ship.</hi> p. 45. l. 15. for 4 <hi>months</hi> r.<hi>a month.</hi> p. 50. l. 24. r. <hi>Out of this Nation. Ibid.</hi> l. 15. r. <hi>Arts Master-peice.</hi> p. 53. l. 33. r. <hi>and ſad, if it do ruin us.</hi> p. 56. l. 23. r. <hi>A loſs</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
